<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of prayers for the dead whether the practice and tradition thereof in the Church be truly Catholick, and a competent evidence of apostolick original and authority? : humbly tendred to the consideration of ...</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08254438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08254438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1241:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of prayers for the dead whether the practice and tradition thereof in the Church be truly Catholick, and a competent evidence of apostolick original and authority? : humbly tendred to the consideration of ...</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers for the dead.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41225:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41225:1"/>
            <p>OF PRAYERS FOR THE DEAD: Whether the <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Tradition</hi> thereof in the CHURCH be truly CATHOLICK, and a competent Evidence of <hi>Apoſtolick Original</hi> and <hi>Authority?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly tendred to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Right Honourable the JUDGES, and of the Gentlemen of the Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the LAW:</p>
            <p>With a PREFACE concerning the <hi>Reaſons</hi> thereof, and the <hi>Concern of the Nation,</hi> that the Differences about Religion be better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, in order to a more firm Foundation of an <hi>Honourable and Laſting PEACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41225:2"/>
            <pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Summers,</hi> Baron of <hi>Eveſham,</hi> Lord High Chancellour of <hi>England;</hi> Sir <hi>John Holt,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> Sir <hi>George Treby,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Common Pleas;</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Ward,</hi> Lord Chief Baron; and the reſt of the Honourable Judges.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Lordſhips.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough at firſt to ſome it may ſeem ſtrange and improper to offer a Theological Controverſie to the Conſideration of Magiſtrates, and Judges of Civil Cauſes; yet if the preſent Conſtitution of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> the Nature of the Queſtion, and the ſpecial Qualifications of the Perſons for the Conſideration of ſuch a Queſtion, beſides the Common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of all States and Perſons in Matters of Religion, be well conſider'd, nothing can be more reaſonable: A <hi>Church</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, and glorying in the Profeſſion, of a Religion Eſtabliſhed by Law; and ſo intirely ſubject to the Authority of the State, that it cannot call a Synode, chooſe a Biſhop, Dean or Prebend, make a Canon, or alter any publick Prayers of the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; a <hi>Queſtion</hi> of Preſcription, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage, and Cuſtom, than which none are more frequently examined, tryed and determined in our Civil Courts; and, by conſequence, no Perſons more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to give a Judgment upon ſuch a Queſtion, becauſe none more verſed and expert in Caſes of that nature than thoſe of the Honourable Profeſſion of the Law. Beſides, Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and the reſt of that Honourable Profeſſion, have another Qualification indiſpenſably requiſite to a juſt and true Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:3"/>
               <hi>Indifferency and Freedom from any ſpecial Prejudice,</hi> more than what is common to the whole Nation, and as much above that as any Perſons in it; I mean that of Education; by which, tho' the inconſiderate Vulgar, and People of little Judgment, are very ſtrangely affected and moved, either fondly affecting, or childiſhly abhorring what hath nothing of real Good or Evil, but what proceeds from an abuſed or deceived Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; yet Men of Parts, Judgment, and Experience can more eaſily extricate themſelves out of the fetters and manacles of ſuch Impreſſions and Prejudice upon conſideration of ſufficient Grounds and Reaſons. But the Generality of the <hi>Engliſh Clergy,</hi> and Non-Conformiſts, are under a double ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and Pre-ingagement: the Authority and Credit of their Party; and their own in particular, having not only imbibed a Special Opinion in the Caſe, but inconſiderately aſſerted, and ſo eſpouſed it alſo, beſides the Prudential Caution of not diſoblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or offending their Auditors: tho' many Proteſtants in other Parts are of another Opinion, and the moſt learned here have deſerted the old Cauſe, both in their Diſputes in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and in their Controverſial Writings. And therefore, as every honeſt Man in any Difference would deſire the Judgment of ſuch as are moſt indifferent, unbyaſſed, and impartial, ſo every wiſe Man will deſire that they may be Perſons of moſt Ability, Skill, and expert in ſuch Matters: And in both theſe reſpects I know none more proper to judge of this Caſe than Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and the Gentlemen of Your Honourable Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all, that You are thus qualified to judge of this matter; but you have alſo a <hi>Concern,</hi> a double Concern in it; but, that it may be fairly and truly determined; a Concern which obligeth you to Impartiality, that the Truth may be cleared, and an End put to ſuch Differences; both in regard to the Places you hold, and the Intereſt you have in the Civil State of the Nation; and in regard of your Perſonal Intereſt and particular Concerns both in this Life and hereafter. For <hi>Matters of Religion</hi> are of no little Importance to the Well-being of States, as well as of
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:3"/>particular Perſons; and to the Well-being of particular Perſons as well in this Life, as hereafter. And all this in a double reſpect; in reſpect to the Providence of God, and in reſpect of their Natural Efficacy and Tendency. It is very manifeſt, that almoſt all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs, Troubles and Diſturbance which this Nation hath ſuffered for more than 150 Years laſt paſt, have proceeded from unhappy <hi>Differences about Matters of Religion:</hi> And it would be as evident, if duly conſidered, that there is as little Likelyhood, if Poſſibility, of any long Continuance of Peace without ſome proper Application to ſo fatal a Root of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief amongst us, for the Extirpation or Suppreſſion of it. Nor is this ſo vain, unreaſonable, or impracticable a thing to be thought on or attempted, as moſt Men are apt to preſume upon the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfulneſs of the Attempts which have been made, if better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd. It is no unuſual thing for Men to learn from the Errors of former Attempts ſo to correct their Methods and Meaſures, as to accompliſh with eaſe what others with great Labour were not able to effect. Many things in Practice are like Riddles in Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, which, after many have found inſoluble by their utmoſt Study, appear at laſt, when the Secret is once revealed, very plain and eaſie to the meaneſt Capacity. But in ſuch Differences as theſe there is uſually <hi>a double Secret;</hi> the one <hi>Supernatural,</hi> managed by inviſible Miniſters of the Divine Providence; the other <hi>Natural and Humane,</hi> proceeding from Error of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or Corruption of the Will and Affections in one or both of the Parties: And for the moſt part there are Faults on both ſides, if not from the beginning, at leaſt in the Progreſs and Continuance of the Difference. For it is no unfrequent thing for ſuch as have a Good Cauſe at firſt, to ſpoil it in the Management.</p>
            <p>And ſuch is the Caſe in theſe Differences in Religion, which have ſo long infeſted this part of the World: Wherein <hi>the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Secret</hi> is the Operation of thoſe Inviſible Powers by the Commiſſion or Permiſſion of God, for Correction of what was and is amiſs in the ſeveral Parties, among whom they aroſe; the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of which belonging more properly to Divines, I ſhall ſay
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:4"/>nothing of it here. But of thoſe Differences, the first and most conſiderable are thoſe between the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and thoſe who pretend a Reformation. And the <hi>Natural and Humane</hi> Secret in them lies in certain Faults on both ſides. The <hi>Faults and Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals of the Papacy and Court of</hi> Rome were ſo groſs and notorious, that all good and intelligent People groaned for a Reformation long before <hi>Luther</hi> was born. But the <hi>Faults of them, who pretended to that Work,</hi> will appear, when well conſidered, no leſs, neither in Number, nor Nature: There is none of them all that is not notoriouſly guilty of Sacrilege, Schiſm and Hereſie; beſides divers <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Practices to promote or maintain their Party. It is even natural to Men to run out of one Extream into the other: and the Evil Spirits, when they are permitted, ceaſe not to inſtigate the corrupt diſpoſition of Men to the utmoſt they can. Hence have proceeded thoſe many endleſs Differences among themſelves, who at firſt differed only from the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> And their Faults and Miſcarriages are ſo notorious, that they are many of them confeſſed, acknowledged, and diſclaimed by divers of the moſt learned of all Parties. The <hi>Engliſh Reformation,</hi> which was not faultleſs before, was farther corrupted by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> (who, tho by ſome magnified as a Martyr, will appear in time to have been ſo miſchievous an Inſtrument both in Church and State, as makes him very unworthy of any honourable Character or Memory in any part of the Catholick Church, but eſpecially that of <hi>England</hi>) and ſettled at laſt thro the prevalence of a Party of <hi>Calvinian</hi> Sectaries, with ſuch Abuſes and Corruptions in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, as the moſt learned and eminent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy have long deſired and indeavoured what they could to rectifie, but have never been able to effect, or ſcarce dared to attempt it in any great Matters, being abuſed and bug-beared with popular Outcries and Imputations of Popery, (with which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation have been very groſsly abuſed) when-ever they dared to aſſert or own any thing of the Primitive Genuine Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity contrary to the Nations of that Faction; who have been pricks in their Eyes, and thorns in their Sides, both to Church and State,
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:4"/>ever ſince, by the juſt Judgment of God, for their Politick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances with the Corruptions of that pretended Reformation; which are in truth much greater than is believed or ſuſpected by many good People, as I may poſſibly, by the Grace of God, ſhew more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in due time.</p>
            <p>But for the preſent, to calm the Minds and ſtop the Mouths of ſuch as may be offended at what I ſay, as briefly as may be, I ſhall only recommend to their Conſideration, if they be <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> the <hi>Expoſtulation</hi> of a late leading Man amongst them, Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter, to the zealous Anti-Papiſts,</hi> which, he ſaith, is <hi>written to try, if it may be, to promote our common Repentance, and to reform the <hi>Dominal Diſtaken Reformation</hi> of thoſe, who have ſinned by</hi> Extreams; <hi>which, by the aſſumed Name of</hi> Reformation <hi>have wronged God, and the Truth, and Mens Souls, with the greater Advantage and Succeſs.</hi> Thus of the Reformation in general in his Book againſt <hi>Foreign Juriſdiction,</hi> printed but little before his Death, <hi>Part 2. ch. 1.</hi> and <hi>ch. 7.</hi> he ſets down together no leſs than ſeven ſummary Heads of Falſe Charges and Wrongs done to the Papiſts by the Sectarian weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed part of Proteſtants, as he elſewhere calls them: <hi>1. Some Men,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do ignorantly charge ſome Errors on the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, which they are not guilty of: 2. or lay the Errors of ſome few upon the moſt: 3. Some make Errors, which are but</hi> de Nomine, <hi>to ſeem to be</hi> de Re: <hi>4. and leſſer Errors to ſeem Great: 5. Some take divers Truths to be Errors: 6. And ſome are ready to call ſome lawful Cuſtoms of the Papiſts by the Name of Popery and Antichriſtian: 7. Some would deny the Papiſts the common Civilities and Liberties which are their due,</hi> &amp;c. And elſewhere he gives us part of a Catalogue of ſuch raſh Charges with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to let us know that thoſe are but part: <hi>How far Proteſtants miſtake and raſhly Charge them in the Doctrines of Predeſtination, Free-will, Grace, Merits, Juſtification, Redemption, Perſeverance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have freely ſhewed in my Catholick Theology, and End of Doctrinal Controverſies, and</hi> Ludovicus le Blank, <hi>after</hi> Others,
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:5"/>
               <hi>hath excellently opened.</hi> Which is a plain Confeſſion that in all thoſe Differences, beſides that about Antichriſt, (which he does not at all approve) the Fault lies on the ſide of the Proteſtants and the Nominal Miſtaken Reformation. And herein I know no Conformiſts, except <hi>Calvinian</hi> Sectaries, who do not agree with him, and thoſe <hi>Others</hi> he mentions. And for <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> they may there ſee, without looking further, that there are and have been many amongst us of <hi>greateſt Reverence and Name,</hi> (as he elſewhere expreſſeth it) who have thought the Differences as unjuſt and unreaſonable on the Proteſtant ſide in divers <hi>other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars;</hi> ſuch as Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Guning,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sparrow,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylyn,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pierce,</hi> Dr. <hi>Saywell,</hi> Dr. <hi>Beveridge,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dodwell;</hi> all whom he particularly names, and indeavours to anſwer: To whom might be added, for my purpoſe, Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Couſens,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Forbes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> and divers other eminent learned Men in and ſince the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> beſides divers now living. And a worthy dignified Clergy-Man of the City, in a Book lately printed, hath aſſerted that the Reformation was, and was to be, but an imperfect Work. By all which it is eaſie to be perceived, that <hi>the Cauſe of the Reformation</hi> is no ſuch clear Cauſe, or infallible Truth, as is generally believed, by thoſe who are educated in ſuch a Preſumption or Perſuaſion: Which might alſo juſtly be ſuſpected from the <hi>Differences,</hi> which aroſe preſently, and have been continued from the beginning with bitter Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions between the Principal Actors in that Work, and their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parties to this day; which are things manifeſt to all People in all Places, where any thing called the Reformation hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed. But there are other Matters very obſervable in this Caſe, as ſeveral <hi>indirect Ends and Motives,</hi> which probably might be, and certainly were the Inducements to many of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners and Promoters of it; the <hi>Irregular Manner</hi> in which it was managed and ſettled; the <hi>ſubtile Accommodations</hi> of the principal parts of the Work to recommend the Preachers, and
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:5"/>gratifie the People, but undermining the Honour of Christ, and the Power of Godlineſs, and ſettling the People in Preſumption and Security upon a Falſe Foundation; according to the Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Apoſtle, <hi>Speaking perverſe things to draw away Diſciples after them;</hi> and the <hi>Fruits and Effects</hi> agreeable thereunto; a plain Indication that it was not of God, but in the Nature of a Judgment, and that they knew not what they did, nor what Spirit they were of: which, tho' certain Truths, and very evident when looked into, yet are not ſo obvious to common Obſervation. Nor indeed, was I my ſelf ſo ſenſible of much of them till after much Study and Indeavours to promote the Service of God, and Good of my Country, it all ſeemed to me to be under <hi>an Enchantment,</hi> ſo that no Good could be done: Whereupon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the <hi>Fruits,</hi> according to our Saviour's Rule, upon a fair Invitation and Opportunity I reſolved upon a Retirement, and a <hi>Review of the Reformation,</hi> the Root which produced no better Fruits: And coming to it with much Sincerity and Impartiality, I ſoon perceived all this that I have here ſaid, and more, very clearly; and ſome things, which relate to the Civil State and preſent Settlement of this Nation; of which I ſoon gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to ſuch Perſons as I thought moſt proper, to acquaint His Majeſty with it; to diſcharge my own Conſcience, what-ever was farther done in it.</p>
            <p>I do not deny but there was <hi>need of a Reformation</hi> of divers things: but none know better than your Lordſhips, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of your Profeſſion, how common a thing it is for Men, who have really a good Cauſe, to make it ill through Paſſion, Partiality, unreaſonable Demands or Charges, and ſuch ill Management as, if it come to Tryal, it muſt be found againſt them; or tho' it be not Good, yet through Partiality or Prejudice to think it Good; and then, when by degrees they have well fixed and rivetted that Opinion, and beſides engaged their Reputation in it, to perſuade themſelves that thoſe things are lawful for the Maintenance of it, which, in truth, are not; and thoſe things uſeful or neceſsary, which, in concluſion, will but expoſe and ruine it: how much Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:6"/>People thus affected frequently bring upon themſelves and others, and endleſs Vexations, when obſtinate in their Opinion, reſolute in their Demands, and pertinacious in their Contentions, right or wrong: how undecent and unbecoming, even in Civil Matters, this appears to all wiſe and good Men, who have Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to obſerve the Truth of the Caſe: On the other ſide, how much more Prudent it is, as well as Juſt and Honeſt, if a Man have the Misfortune to purchaſe an ill Title, or be unhappily concerned in an ill Cauſe, to indeavour to make it Good by fair Agreement with Parties concerned, and Tender of what is juſt and reaſonable; and ſuch honeſt Means as will at leaſt ſecure his Reputation, if not his Cauſe alſo, however much mend the matter. This has been always <hi>my Practice,</hi> and this I am reſolved to do in this Caſe, of what I have diſcover'd upon my Review aforeſaid: I do utterly diſclaim all the Iniquity of the Caſe that I have already diſcovered, or can diſcover, all the Sacrilege, Schiſm, and Hereſie, and other Corruptions of the pretended Reformation in general, and of that of <hi>England</hi> in particular. And tho' I do not forſake the Corruptions of this Church to eſpouſe thoſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet I think fit to make my own Cauſe good, and to ſtand only upon ſuch Terms, as I can comfortably refer to the Goodneſs and Mercy of God, and as I am ſatisfied will make it their Faults, not mine, who ſhall refuſe Agreement and Communion with me. What I think prudent in my own Caſe, if it be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I could wiſh the whole Nation did ſee it as well as I: For I believe it a more <hi>firm Foundation for a laſting Peace</hi> and true Happineſs than any other we can build upon. And if I be not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in <hi>the Matters in Difference,</hi> there is ſcarce any but ſuch, as many principal Men of the one ſide think ought to be yielded by them, or as all on the other confeſs may, for just Cauſe, be granted by them; or may be otherwiſe accommodated by only fit Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and Expreſſions. To which, ſince the moſt conſiderable on both ſides have ſhewed a very good Diſpoſition, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Precepts of the Goſpel, and the Peace, and Repoſe, and Common Good of Mankind, eſpecially in this part of the World,
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:6"/>which may have a great Influence upon the reſt, do require it; I believe it would be for the Honour and Interest of which ſide ſoever ſhould do it, to make the Propoſal, provided it be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry juſt and reaſonable. Of thoſe Matters, which are thought ought to be yielded, this, which I propoſe to your Lordſhips Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, concerning the ancient Practice of <hi>Prayers for the Dead,</hi> is one, and the moſt proper Inſtance that can be in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. It is indeed a double Inſtance; for it is a plain Evidence, that one of the principal Suppoſitions, with which not only Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of People in theſe laſt Ages, but ever ſince the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, have been deceived and miſted, with very plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pretence, is notwithſtanding falſe in it ſelf, beſides falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious miſapplications of what is true: as appears abundantly by <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian,</hi> and the Common Practice of the Ancient Chriſtians in their Conteſts with Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. And it is in its ſelf one of the greateſt Inſtances of the Power of Prejudice to abuſe weak Men out of their apparent Interest, without any other competent ground or reaſon; of the Weakneſs of Men to be ſo abuſed; and of the Inconſiderateneſs of thoſe who preſume to be poſitive, and direct others in ſuch Caſes, that I know of.</p>
            <p>My intention at firſt was to have publiſhed <hi>a Vindication of the True</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liturgy,</hi> the first Book of <hi>Ed. 6.</hi> compoſed by known <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy-Men, and afterward corrupted and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and a Faction of Foreigners, and other unknown <hi>Calvinian</hi> Sectaries in Secret, and ſo craftily impoſed upon the Church and Nation. But when I conſidered, in theſe unhappy Differences, how partially Zealous the Generality of Clergy-Men (who have any Zeal at all) are for their own Party, more than for the common Concerns of Religion, or of their Country; and how unconcerned the chief of the Clergy of this Nation are, and have been ever ſince the State aſſumed the Supream Power of Eccleſiaſtical Matters, as if either diſpirited, or preſuming that the Care alſo is incumbent only upon them who have aſſumed the Power; and how little I have found, by Experience, is to be
<pb n="*⁎*" facs="tcp:41225:7"/>expected from them; and, on the other ſide, how neceſſary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is for the Peace and Repoſe of this Nation, that the Occaſions of ſuch miſchievous Diſſentions ſhould be better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and removed; I preſently perceived I had a fair Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity in this to preſent a proper inſtance of a Matter of ſuch Importance to Perſons as well qualified to judge, and who were likely to be as ſenſible of the Importance of it, as any; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon concluded to preſent it alone to the Conſideration of Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and the Gentlemen of Your Honourable Profeſſion; having already, as to the reſt, made a conſiderable <hi>Experiment</hi> of what I have here ſaid, of the <hi>Hopes</hi> we may have <hi>of a good Succeſs,</hi> if they, to whom it doth belong, will but do what is in their Power towards it: For having publiſhed a Liturgy, Entituled, <hi>The Liturgy of the Ancients repreſented,</hi> as near as well may be, <hi>in Engliſh Forms,</hi> not much different (only a little more compleat) from that Reſtitution of the True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy attempted by the <hi>Scotch,</hi> with the Aſſiſtance of the Principal of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops, <hi>Anno 1637.</hi> I preſented it to ſome of the principal learned Men firſt of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who much approved it, and wiſhed it reſtored by Law; then of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> who alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it, and declared their Satisfaction to communicate in that Form; and, at laſt, of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> who had no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions to the Matter or Form of it. And, in ſhort, to ſay the Truth, the Abuſe and Corruptions of the Publick Liturgy in theſe two particulars, <hi>Of Prayers for the Dead,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice,</hi> to mention nothing more, are ſo groſs and notorious, that they alone are ſufficient to make the <hi>Church of England</hi> inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably Guilty of Schiſm, and juſtly obnoxious to Excommunication, (which may be the Enchantment it ſeems to lie under) and unſafe for any pious Perſon, after notice, to hold Communion with it: ſo that it ſeems not only expedient and prudent for the State to conſider theſe Matters, (for otherwiſe nothing is to be expected from theſe Biſhops) but abſolutely neceſsary: And ſo I leave it with Your Lordſhips.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41225:7"/>
            <head>Of the Practice of Prayers for the DEAD <hi>In the Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Performance of any <hi>good Offices for the Dead,</hi> even to their Bodies, their Bones, their Memories, their Wills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath always been reputed a very commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable thing among all civilized Nations; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath been acted to the contrary, barbarous, and inhumane; and the only Neglect of ſuch Offices by ſuch as were under any ſpecial Obligation, of evil conſequence; as if Mankind had ſome ſecret ſenſe that Separate Souls were ſenſible of the Kindneſs or Unkindneſs of thoſe who ſurvived them, and had ſome power to gratifie or revenge the Kindneſs or Injuries, eſpecially of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and ſuch as they had any ſpecial Intereſt in in their Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. And if ſuch inferior Offices to their Bodies and Memories have been ſo reputed, much more may ſuch good Offices, as <hi>Prayers for the Souls departed,</hi> deſerve commendation. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it hath been always commonly <hi>practiſed, by all Nations, Gentiles, Jews, Mahometans,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and that without any known Beginning: but very probably by <hi>Tradition from the common
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Matters tranſmitted from them, and received and conſerved by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> See Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi>'s 2d Letter, § 8.</note> Parents of Mankind,</hi> being very agreeable to Nature, and confirmed by Apparitions.</p>
            <p>And certainly this is a thing ſo <hi>innocent,</hi> ſo <hi>free from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of Evil, ſo deſirable both for ones ſelf and their Friends, that it is very ſtrange that any, eſpecially good People, ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, nay frighted from it; and much more that any ſhould ſo preſume, upon their own Opinion and Conceit, as to offer to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41225:8"/>them ſo contrary to the Practice of the whole World in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and of the whole Catholick Church, without clearer Evidence in ſo obſcure a Caſe, as is that of the middle State of Souls to us Mortals: which is not to be believed could ever have been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſecret Energy of thoſe Powers of Darkneſs, which have effected greater Miſchiefs than this by the ſame Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>the Practice of the Jews</hi> at this day, and has been ſo without any known beginning: was ſo before our Saviour's time, as appears by the Book of <hi>Maccabces,</hi> and their ancient <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> which, 'tis ſaid, they uſed in the Captivity, ſtill extant in their <hi>Talmud;</hi> and never was reproved by our Saviour, or any of his Apoſtles, or of the Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>the Practice of the whole Catholick Church</hi> at this day, and of all Chriſtians, except ſuch as according to the unanimous Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Ancients are gone, and are, out of it; and hath been ſo without any known beginning, in their moſt ſolemn Worſhip; ſo that no Church can be aſſigned where they, who ſcruple at it now, could have had Communion without it: And never was <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,</hi> contradicted, or queſtioned by any one of any Reputation in the Catholick Church; or by any one at all for near 400 years.</p>
            <p>The firſt, who is known to have queſtioned it, was <hi>Aerius,</hi> in the time of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> a Presbyter, a frantick, proud, conceited Man, diſcontented becauſe he could not get a Biſhoprick, and thereupon, 'tis probable, quarrelled not only at divers Practiſes of the Church, but at Epiſcopacy it ſelf: an ill Man by the Judgement of all; and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> reckon him in their Catalogues of Hereticks for his Oppoſition of this Practice eſpecially.</p>
            <p>The next, whoſe Teſtimony is produced in this Cauſe, is one <hi>Stephanus Gobarus,</hi> and obſcure Scribler, and a confeſſed Heretick, even by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> who alleadgeth his Teſtimony, as well as by <hi>Photius,</hi> from whom he takes it, and who gives this Character of his Book, that it ſeems a Work of much Labour, but little Profit; and a Study rather of Applauſe and Vain-Glory, than any great Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It was a Collection of the different Sentences of the Fathers in divers points of Doctrine, and alleadged to prove ſuch a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Opinions in this Caſe, and what was the true Sentence of the Church. A ſpecial Witneſs, and to much purpoſe! an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick to prove the true Sentence of the Church! and a vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Perſon, who, out of Oſtentation of Parts and Learning, ſeeks for Differences in the Fathers, and ſets himſelf up for a Judge!
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41225:8"/>which he might, if he had pleaſed, have done alſo in the Scripture it ſelf. But after all he doth not ſo much as declare his Opinion in the principal Queſtion in this Caſe, but only in a by-point. A poor Cauſe that ſtands in need of ſuch Supports!</p>
            <p>If we ſet him aſide, as well we may, who is neither a competent Witneſs of the Sentence of the Church, nor doth declare his own in this Caſe, we find not another in near 700 years after <hi>Aerius,</hi> till <hi>Peter de Bruis,</hi> and one <hi>Henricus,</hi> a runagate Monk, who took up a Trade of Preaching, and ſpent what he got in Gaming, and on Harlots: They denied alſo the Baptiſm of Infants, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sacrifice, Publick Churches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt them <hi>Petrus Clunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis,</hi> a Man eminent for Learning and Sanctity, wrote, and St. <hi>Bernard</hi> preached, and confirmed his Doctrine with ſo great a Miracle, as convinced Multitudes, who had been ſeduced by them.</p>
            <p>After theſe aroſe one <hi>Waldo,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>Lions,</hi> very rich, but unlearned, who probably had a Zeal for God, but not according to Knowledge, and attributing too much to his own Opinion, procured certain Books to be written in his own Language, and diſtributing his Eſtate among the Poor, took upon him the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Office of Preaching, and began the Sect, called after his own Name, <hi>Waldenſes;</hi> and from their Place and Quality, <hi>The Poor of Lions.</hi> Among other Heterodox Opinions, (whereof ſome were peculiar to their own Sect, and diſallowed by all others) this of rejecting Prayers for the Dead was one.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtolici</hi> of that time, I ſuppoſe, were not a diſtinct Sect, but the ſame, who aſſumed that Name. And the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> who in the next Century encreaſed very much, till by the ſecular Power and force of Arms they were ſuppreſſed, ſeem to have been a Branch of the ſame Root; however, in this particular they agreed, as they did in moſt others.</p>
            <p>Since thoſe, I know not any Sect which hath ariſen, and which queſtioned or contradicted Prayers for the Dead, till thoſe which have ſprung out of what is called <hi>the Reformation:</hi> For I do not find that <hi>Wickelif,</hi> and his Followers here, <hi>the Lollards,</hi> or <hi>John Huſs,</hi> or <hi>Hierom of Prague,</hi> who carried his Books and Doctrines into their own Country, and were all three Men of Parts and Learning, ever oppoſed Prayers for the Dead, tho' among the Opinions attributed to <hi>Huſs,</hi> one is, that there is <hi>no Purgatory Fire;</hi> which is denied by others, who yet are for Prayers for the Dead. But by all the ſeveral Sects of <hi>the later Reformers, ſince Luther</hi> began,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41225:9"/>they have been queſtioned, oppoſed, and left out of their Publick Prayers.</p>
            <p>Only here in <hi>England,</hi> in the firſt Liturgy, compoſed by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> 6. which I therefore call <hi>The True Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> the ancient Prayers for the Dead were retained, both in the moſt Solemn Office of the Daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and at Funerals: But theſe and other principal Parts of the Liturgy were ſoon after new-modelled in a clandeſtine manner by <hi>Cranmer, Bucer,</hi> and other Foreigners, and <hi>Calvinian</hi> Sectaries; and craftily impoſed upon the Church and Nation: And the Abuſe is continued to this day.</p>
            <p>This is the true <hi>Original and Succeſſion of all the Oppoſition</hi> which hath ever been made to this Practice, of all Mankind in general, and of the whole Catholick Church of Chriſt; by Hereticks, Sectaries, and Schiſmaticks, and the meaneſt of all thoſe; not a Man amongſt them of any Eminence for Piety, or any Virtue, or ſo much as Parts or Learning: much leſs any Man of Note in the Church: much leſs any Church, Party, or Part of the Catholick Church, who were, or who continued in Communion with The Catholick Church, or any Particular Catholick Church, as they anciently diſtinguiſh'd them from the Aſſemblies and Aſſociations of Hereticks, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks in the ſame City. It is very obſervable, wonderful, and a great Evidence of unqueſtionable or undeniable Truth, that in ſo many Ages, when there had been ſo many ſo conſiderable Parties of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and ſo malicious, ſpiteful, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, as many of them were againſt the Church, that none of the moſt conſiderable of them ſhould ever ſeek to advantage their Cauſe by ſuch a Queſtion; which doubtleſs they would not have failed to have done, had they apprehended any color of Truth or Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in it: that none in all the Parts of the World ſhould ever oppoſe it but ſuch an obſcure, inconſiderate and inconſiderable Generation of People, till the late Reformers ſprung up, who thought they could never reform enough, or pick quarrels too much, till they had brought that, which might have been a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Cauſe, if well laid and managed, to an indefenſible brable. Amongſt them indeed there have been many Men of ſufficient Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but, but few of that Ingenuity, Impartiality, freedom from Prejudice, temporal Intereſt, or Fear of Diſpleaſing, and of that Generoſity, as to aſſert the Truth plainly, without reſpect of Perſons or Parties: and thoſe few have been very much born down
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41225:9"/>(among us eſpecially) by the Violence and Headineſs of Parties and Factions. Yet ſuch is the Power and Evidence of Truth in this Caſe, that it hath found Advocates amongſt the moſt learned of all Parties.</p>
            <p>Of this I think it not improper to produce an inſtance or two in this Place: The firſt ſhall be an eminent Perſon both for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Virtue, Biſhop <hi>Forbes,</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Edenburg,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. who is reported to have ſaid of him, That he had found out a Biſhop, who deſerved that a See ſhould be made for him. In his <hi>Conſiderationes Modeſtae, Controverſiâ de Purgatorio,</hi> cap. 3. §. 17. coming to ſpeak of Prayers and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Dead; <hi>Sed hic primum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But here first,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is to be reproved the Opinion of ſome rigid Proteſtants, who do altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cenſure and condemn Prayers for the Dead; becauſe they find no Precept or Example of ſuch Prayers in the Old or New Teſtament. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly even thoſe, who are moſt againſt it, dare not deny that it is a moſt ancient Cuſtom, and moſt (univerſally) received in the whole Church of Christ, that in the Publick Prayers of the Church Commemoration ſhould be made for the Dead, and Reſt be prayed for to God for thoſe who died piouſly, and in the Peace of the Church.</hi> And having cited divers of the Ancients for it, he adds: <hi>This moſt ancient Cuſtom was full of Piety, and moſt truly did</hi> Caſſander <hi>ſay,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>This was always fixt in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Note.</hi> Then this was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among All.</note> All Chriſtian Minds, That the Spirits of thoſe, who being initiated in the Sacrament of Christ, departed this Life in the Confeſſion of his Name, with ſignification of Repentance, ſhould be commended to the Mercy of God, that Remiſſion of Sin, Eternal Reſt, and a Part with the Elect, might be intreated for them.
<note n="†" place="margin">This ſecond part is ſo ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, p.</hi> 246. as is apt to lead the Reader into miſtake, as if they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in more than the Author did intend.</note> And altho' concerning that State of Souls, for which thoſe things were profitable, it was neither ſufficiently manifeſt, nor agreed among all, yet all judged this Office, as a Teſtimony of Charity toward the Deceaſed, and a Profeſſion of Faith concerning the Immortality of Souls, and Reſurrection to come, to be grateful to God, and profitable to the Church.</hi>
               </q> Then he ſaith, <hi>This moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Cuſtom of the Church very many and moſt learned Proteſtants do not diſallow;</hi> and cites the <hi>Apology</hi> of the <hi>Augsburg Confeſſ. Chemnicius, Mentſerus, Luther, Gerard, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus Regius, Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius, Voſſius,</hi> Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> and paſſing over in ſilence very many others, as he ſaith, he recites the Words of the Liturgy of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. both in the Office for the Communion, and that for Burials; laments that ſuch moſt ancient and pious Prayers ſhould, by the Perſuaſion of <hi>Bucer,</hi> and others, be expunged; and wiſheth that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which hath ſhewed great Moderation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41225:10"/>in many other things of leſs moment, had rather conformed her ſelf in this buſineſs, as alſo in ſome others, to the moſt ancient Cuſtom of the Univerſal Church, than for ſome Errors and Abuſes, which had by degrees crept in, plainly rejected it, and wholly taken it away, to the great Scandal of almoſt all other Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>I need add no more after this Learned and Apoſtolick Biſhop, only, in ſhort, take notice of what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus Regius</hi> ſaith, that <hi>None reject it but Epicureans and Sadduces;</hi> and <hi>Vorſtius,</hi> that <hi>No Good Man can diſlike it;</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> that <hi>There is little that can be ſaid against it;</hi> and conclude this matter with the Words of the learned and famous <hi>Hugo Grotius; The uſe of Praying for the Dead, received through all Churches of the Eaſt, no leſs than of the Weſt, ought not to be condemned.</hi> And after ſome reaſons for it, and ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Jews,</hi> he adds, <hi>The Ancient Liturgies are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, ſince Christ himſelf did never reprehend the Prayers for the Dead, commonly uſed among the Jews; of which there is a Form extant in the Talmud, made, as is believed, in the Babylonian Captivity, and mentioned in the ſecond Book of the</hi> Maccabees.</p>
            <p>It will be replied, That as great a Man, and of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as any of thoſe, hath written againſt it, the famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armath.</hi> It is very true he hath, and imployed and ſtrained all his Learning, all his Parts, and all his Skill, and a little too much, to oppoſe it; and all to very little purpoſe for his own Cauſe, but to very good purpoſe againſt it: For it is a great Evidence and Demonſtration of what Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> truly ſaid, That <hi>there is little that can be ſaid againſt what this great Man takes ſuch pains to oppoſe.</hi> The ſole Queſtion between him and his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary was, <hi>Whether the Fathers of the firſt</hi> 400 <hi>or</hi> 500 <hi>Years held that Prayer for the Dead is both commendable and godly?</hi> as appears by the Challenge, which was in thoſe very Words, and no other. How, and where, doth he anſwer this plain Queſtion? His Title of that part of his Anſwer is general, <hi>Of Prayer for the Dead.</hi> He ſaw well enough how little he had to ſay to that plain Queſtion; and therefore reſolved to take more Liberty, to ſay ſomething of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Title, tho little or nothing to the Queſtion. He ſpends three ſcore and ten pages upon the general matter; but, if I miſtake not, not ten lines directly and cloſely to the ſpecial Queſtion.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>To uſe his own words</hi> p. 170. <hi>He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities to blear Mens Eyes with all; which being narrowly look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into will be found nothing at all to the purpoſe.</hi>
               </note> Which is to abuſe, not ſo much his Adverſary, as his Reader, with a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious appearance of an Anſwer, which, in truth and reality, is nothing to the purpoſe. That which comes neareſt to the purpoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41225:10"/>is what he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 246. <q>
                  <hi>Theſe Two Queſtions,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be diſtinguiſhed:</hi> Whether Prayers and Oblations were to be made for the Dead? <hi>and,</hi> Whether the Dead did receive any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Profit thereby? <hi>In the latter of theſe, he</hi> (the Reader) <hi>ſhall find great Difference among the Doctors: in the former, very little, or none at all.</hi>
               </q> This is indeed to the purpoſe: but his Reſolution of the former Queſtion, tho' very true, is a plain Confeſſion againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For if they be agreed that Prayers and Oblations were to be made for the Dead, then certainly they held that that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and godly; which is all that his Adverſary did affirm then, and that I do principally aſſert now: for what I have to alleadge farther, is but a Conſequence of that. And his Reſolution of the latter Queſtion is manifeſtly falſe, and a diſingenuous Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for if among ſo great a number of Doctors in ſo many Years he could have aſſigned five, or ſix, or ten, who had really differed in that point from the reſt, (which thoſe few he cites rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood did not) had that been a <hi>Great Difference?</hi> And if ſome Authors do ſay, that ſome, or that many, in their time, were doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the point, is that a ſufficient proof that it <hi>was ſtill a Queſtion in the Church?</hi> when they name not one Perſon in particular, much leſs any Doctor, nor tell us ſo much as of what quality they were, who had thoſe Doubts. When <hi>a Difference</hi> is <hi>Great,</hi> there muſt be ſome proportion between the Contenders: and where a <hi>Queſtion</hi> is continued, there muſt be ſome Diſputes, Contention, or Debates. But if Peoples ſecret <hi>Doubts</hi> muſt be taken for <hi>Queſtions in the Church,</hi> that is the ready way to bring all Religion into queſtion: and it is not to be doubted but ſuch dealings in Controverſies hath had its ſhare in producing this growth of Scepticiſm and Atheiſm of late. That ſuch a Man as this ſhould put Colours upon Cauſes; ſhould hold up Contentions; ſhould be ſo addicted to Parties, as in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them to confirm People in Opinions, which if falſe are miſchievous, and if true of little Advantage, and contrary to ſo great Authority as is on the other ſide; and ſo expoſe his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Integrity, is a great Unhappineſs to himſelf, and a Scandal to others.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible, what others may have obſerved in this great Man (for 'tis a ſcurvy thing to be ingaged in an ill Cauſe) may have taught them more Wiſdom; for, for ought I can find, as well in the Controverſial Writings of late, as in the Diſputations at the Univerſity, the Old Cauſe, <hi>An Preces pro Defunctis ſint Licitae?</hi> is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41225:11"/>quite deſerted, and that Queſtion is turned into another, <hi>An Preces pro Defunctis antiquitus uſurpatae inferant Purgatorium Papiſticum?</hi> It is well Men have learned ſo much Wiſdom for themſelves, as to mend their Cauſe ſo far as that; and it is to be wiſhed, that they may alſo learn ſo much Honeſty, as to undeceive the People, and reſtore to them, for themſelves and their Friends, the Comfort and Benefit of that ancient Catholick Practice. Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi> one of the learnedſt Perſons this Church hath produc'd, and a <hi>late Biſhop of St. Aſaph,</hi> have done well to do what they could, and reſtore it upon their own Tomb-ſtones, tho' they could not do it in the Church: and if all who believe well, would but do ſo well, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs what they believe, which certainly they ought to do, we ſhould ſoon ſee the Truth revive and flouriſh beyond Expectation; and ſo, much of our Contentions abated.</p>
            <p>Thus concerning the Perſons who have oppoſed this Practice, and ſet up themſelves againſt the Authority of the whole Catholick Church. I come now to conſider <hi>the Oppoſition it ſelf,</hi> their Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Reaſons. Such is the Wit of Man, and the Subtilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that ſcarce any Truth is ſo evident, but they can find out ſome ſpecious Appearances to ſet up againſt it. But ſuch is the Mercy and Wiſdom of God, that he hath provided ſufficient means for Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for all ſuch as keep within the Bounds of Humility and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; that is, in Subjection not only of their Wills, but alſo of their Intellects and Underſtandings, to his Orders, Ordinances and Preſcriptions, the very Buſineſs of their Lives in this World, for Preparation for another. And to ſuch, beſides the Common Means, he will kindly vouchſafe a ſpecial Guidance ſufficient for their Circumſtances. Of the Danger our Saviour and his Apoſtles have given to all fair Warning, and great Caution; acquainting us with the End, why the moſt Wiſe and Gracious God permits it, for Tryal and Exerciſe; the Danger and Subtilty of the Miniſters of Satan, ſuch as ſhould deceive, if it were poſſible, the very Elect; the ſpecial Marks to know and avoid them, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Fruits, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pretences, (Sheeps Clothing,) and Diſtraction and Diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among themſelves, crying, <hi>Here is Christ, and There is Chriſt;</hi> and ſpecial Directions, <hi>Believe them not, Go not out after them.</hi> All this Proviſion hath the Devil attempted to undermine, partly by raiſing real Scandals and Offences, and partly by ſtrongly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Imaginary ones. But againſt all this Humility and Charity will fortifie us; and the Grace, ſpecial Guidance and Mercy of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41225:11"/>God will preſerve us, if we be careful to continue in thoſe Graces. It was Pride, and Arrogance, and Diſcontent in <hi>Aerius,</hi> which gave the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Epiphan. p.</hi> 905. <hi>a.</hi>
               </note> Devil Advantage to inſtigate him to the firſt Oppoſition of ſuch a Catholick Practice. It was Pride, Vanity, and Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Parts, by which he ſet <hi>Gobarus</hi> to work to ſhew his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Acuteneſs in finding out Differences of Opinions among them, who perhaps in many of thoſe things differed no more than the Writers of the Sacred Scriptures ſeem to do. For I do not find that he made any ſpecial Oppoſition againſt this Practice. But I doubt it was not imaginary, but real Scandal and groſs Abuſes of a good Practice, by which <hi>Waldo</hi> and his Followers, and the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> were moved to oppoſe all without Diſtinction: tho' there ſeems to have been in him, with a Zeal for God, but without Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, a Mixture of Pride and Conceitedneſs. And it was real, and not imaginary Scandal, by which <hi>Luther</hi> was at firſt moved to oppoſe Indulgencies, and his Followers at firſt to oppoſe even this innocent and commendable Practice. But in ſuch Men as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> it was the Reputation of the Cauſe they had eſpouſed in groſs, and Compliances with the Times, and their particular Intereſts, by which they were moved. But let us but carefully follow our Saviour's Admonitions and Directions, wiſely diſtinguiſh the Ingredients of the Compoſition of Truth and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and honeſtly imbrace, hold faſt, and own the Truth, when we have the Opportunity, and we ſhall not want ſufficient Light and Evidence to find it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſpecious Appearances</hi> ſet up againſt this Catholick Practice of the Church of Chriſt are theſe: 1. That there is no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Authority for it. 2. That the Ancient Practice was to Pray for all, ſuch as were at Reſt. 3. That the Ancients were not agreed in their Opinions concerning the State of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Souls, or the general Intention of the Church in thoſe Prayers.</p>
            <p>To detect the Fallacy, Falſity, and Impertinence of theſe Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, as briefly as may be: To the <hi>firſt,</hi> I ſay, it is a meer Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and grounded upon a falſe Suppoſition, that nothing is to be admitted in Doctrine or Worſhip but what there is <hi>Scripture Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> for, if it be underſtood of a <hi>ſpecial Authority;</hi> and their uſual Pretences of not Adding, or Diminiſhing, are to be underſtood of thoſe particular Parts or Books of the Scripture, as is plain by the Additional Writings and Practices of Holy Men afterwards. 2. It
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41225:12"/>is inconſiſtent with the Tradition of the Doctrine, and Inſtitutions of the Goſpel, and of the Ordinances of the Apoſtles, which were all by Word and Deed, without Writing, as the Common Laws of this Nation were at firſt ſettled: and much of what was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, was written upon ſpecial Occaſions, and much with that Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Conciſeneſs, by the ſpecial Providence of God, as was ſufficient for them for whom it was intended, and yet ſo as ſhould need an Authentick Explication to preſerve the Authority of the Catholick Church. 3. It is contrary to the expreſs Directions of the Scripture, to contend for the Doctrine once delivered to the Saints, in general, and to hold the Traditions they had received, whether by Word, or Epiſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if it be underſtood of a <hi>general Authority,</hi> the Allegation it ſelf is falſe: For it is contrary to all thoſe Scriptures, which declare the Authority of the Church, and require Obedience to Superiors: And either way it is contrary to the Sentiments, Teſtimony, and Practice of the Ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who, in Queſtions of Difficulty and Conteſts with Hereticks, always inquired, not only what was written by the Apoſtles, but alſo, or principally, what was delivered by them to the Churches, which they founded, in all Parts of the World, of which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church doth conſiſt, which the Scripture it ſelf ſtiles the Pillar and Baſis of Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. v. <hi>Grot.</hi> not only for the Senſe and Meaning of the Scripture, as Lawyers, with good reaſon do, when in doubts about the Conſtruction of Writings they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how the Uſage hath gone; for in that caſe the Writing is the Principal Evidence: but in this caſe, what was delivered to the Churches, which were compleatly and plainly inſtructed and ordered by the Apoſtles, was the principal Inquiry, and the Scriptures but an acceſſory Evidence, as our Year-Books are of the Common Law, in Queſtions concerning the Common Law. But I doubt not but there was a ſpecial Providence in it, that ſo much was written, and no more, and that it was written in ſuch a manner. Laſtly, This hath been the Practice and <hi>Pretence of Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> in all Ages, to the intent with the better colour to ſet aſide the Authority of the Catholick Church, that they might ſo make way to ſet up their own private Opinions and Conceits in the Place thereof; but never more groſsly, nauciouſly, and ſcandalouſly, than by ſome of the Principal of the late Reformers, <hi>Calvin</hi> eſpecially, on the one ſide, inculcating and crying up <hi>The Pure Word of God, The Pure Word of God;</hi> and on the other, abuſing it, by ſtraining
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41225:12"/>wreſting it to ſerve their own turns, and eluding and evading what is plainly contrary to them; which is now paſt all doubt, not only by the Confeſſions of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>Le Blank,</hi> but the many of all Parties, who have deſerted divers of thoſe Aſſertions, which were ſo hotly contended for under that ſpecious Pretence: a plain Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Demonſtration that they were no better than their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors in that Pretence. But beſides all this, what I am now doing, if I be not much miſtaken, will be a particular demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth of what I ſay.</p>
            <p>To <hi>the other two Allegations,</hi> I ſay, they are both <hi>impertinent</hi> to the Queſtion under conſideration here; which is only concerning the Matter of Fact and Practice; I do not ſay that they are impertinent to the Subject in general, to be conſidered upon other Occaſions; but to this ſpecial Queſtion: and therefore to inſiſt upon them in this Caſe, inſtead of directly anſwering to the Queſtion, is fallacious, captious, and an abuſe to the Reader, to impoſe upon him, diſtract him, and withdraw him from the proper Queſtion. There might be Difference in Forms, and various Intendments, and all conſiſtent. Certainly there was no ſuch Difference or Variety either of Forms or Intendment, as there is this day amongſt Proteſtants of both, in their greateſt Solemnity of the Sacrament. But if the matter of Fact be certain, it may be in the Power of the Church to order the Form, and at Liberty for every one to conſtrue the Intention, or make his Inferences or Obſervations for his own Uſe, as well as of the Scripture. And the Matter of Fact is granted by the very Allegation: Nor indeed is it much denied by any Men of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Scio eſſe pervetuſtam hanc precandi pro piè defunctis conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bucer</hi> in his Cenſure; and after he had a little indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to put off <hi>Tertullian,</hi> S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> he adds, <hi>Sed ſit hic quantumvis vetuſtus Dionyſius; Et ſit hujus atque aliorum S. Patrum authoritas quantumlibet magna: attamen noſtrum est tanto anteferre omni humanae authoritati divinam, quanto Deus omni homine major eſt, &amp; ſapientia, &amp; noſtri charitate, docendique nos omnia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſione. Jam or are pro Defunctis nullae docent Scripturae, ſive verbo, ſive exemplo. Et vetitum eſt quicquid his adjicere vel detrahere,</hi> Deut. 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>Solet nobis objici,</hi> ſays <hi>Peter Martyr, Eccleſiam ſemper pro De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functis oraſſe; quod quidem non inficior; ſed aſſero illius facti, neque Verbi Dei, neque Exempli, quod deſumitur ex Sacris literis auctoritatem habere, in</hi> 1 Cor. 3. fol. 45. Ed. Tig. 1579. <hi>Verum eſt quod Papiſtae aiunt,</hi> ſays <hi>Bullinger,</hi> Dec. 4. Ser. 10. <hi>Veteres oraſſe &amp; ſacrificaſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41225:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>pro Defunctis: Scio quid Doctor Eccleſiae Inſignis Auguſtinus, quid Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiſſimus Chryſoſtomus, aliique viri vetuſti ac clari hac de re ſcriptum relinquerunt: Sed quaero num hi rectè fecerunt? Scio damnatum fuiſſe Aerium, quod hujuſmodi Orationes &amp; Oblationes improbaret. Afferunt ſecundum Maccabaeorum librum: Sed is nihil probat, cum non ſit Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus: Adjiciunt &amp; Traditionem Apoſtolicam: Sed mihi id non videtur; nec illi unquam in ſcriptis ita praecipiunt.</hi> This is the Sum of the Caſe, and honeſtly ſaid; and therefore I ſhall conclude this part with it.</p>
            <p>Such is the Folly, Paſſion, and Inconſiderateneſs of Men, that they many times bring ſuch Cauſes to Tryal, as upon their own ſhewing, and hearing their own Evidence only, appears to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent and indifferent Perſons to be againſt them. And ſuch I believe will this Cauſe of theſe Men appear to be to all competent Judges, without more a do. Notwithſtanding, for the more plain and full Conviction and Satisfaction of ſuch as are leſs intelligent and more ſcrupulous; and that thoſe Honourable Perſons, to whoſe Conſideration I preſent it, may themſelves judge of the Evidences, which extort theſe Confeſſions from ſuch as would elude them if they could, I will produce ſo much as is ſufficient for the purpoſe: and that I be not tedious, I will forbear all that, which would prove it to have been a true Catholick Practice of the whole Church for above 1200 years laſt paſt, and confine my ſelf to the time allowed and approved by the Church and State of <hi>England,</hi> that is, the time of the firſt four
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Of</hi> Nice, <hi>Anno</hi> 325. 2. Conſtant. <hi>Anno</hi> 381. 3. Epheſus, <hi>Anno</hi> 431. 4. Chalced, <hi>Anno</hi> 481.</note> general Councils, and that preceeding to the time of the Apoſtles; that is, from that to the Year of our Lord 451.</p>
            <p>As for the ſucceeding Ages, to this day, that it was obſerved all along <hi>per totum Orbem,</hi> and therefore believed to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the Apoſtles, as the moſt ancient Writers upon the Church Offices affirm, I preſume no Man will deny; and therefore I ſhall only mention one Obſervation concerning thoſe Ages: I have made all the Search that poſſibly I could, both by Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts and printed Books, to diſcover the moſt ancient Forms of celebrating the Holy Euchariſt in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church: and tho' I have met with divers Variations in other parts, yet I never could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any Alteration in that that is the principal part, and as Dr. <hi>Barlow,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> ſays, <hi>the moſt innocent part</hi> of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office, called <hi>The Canon of the Maſs,</hi> ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, nor indeed by him <gap reason="illegible: overwritten" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> believe the whole Canon is not of leſs Antiquity than <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> or S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> if not much ancienter, divers particulars of it being found in more ancient
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41225:13"/>Authors. It is not long ſince a very Reverend and Learned Biſhop, ſince deceaſed, ſpeaking to me of it, ſaid, it was <hi>a Noble piece of Antiquity;</hi> and Dr. <hi>Barlow</hi> hath left under his hand a juſt Cenſure of one who cut that part out of an ancient Miſſel at <hi>Oxford,</hi> for an ignorant half learned Fellow. This alone is an ample Evidence of the Practice of all the <hi>Latin</hi> Churches for theſe Ages; which, from thence, I ſhall indeavour to trace back to its Original.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and S <hi>Paulinus</hi> both lived within the time preſcribed, and died 20 years before the laſt of the ſaid four Councils, about <hi>An.</hi> 431. S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was a Perſon of great Natural parts, acquired Learning, Piety, Holineſs, and of great Authority and Reputation in the whole Catholick Church, eſpecially in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, of which he is reckoned one of the chiefeſt Doctors. He had in his younger time taught Rhetorick at <hi>Rome,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Millan,</hi> ſo that he was acquainted with the World, as well as with Books, and every way as well qualified to bear his Teſtimony in the Caſe as poſſibly could be. S. <hi>Paulinus</hi> was a Perſon of great Quality and Eſtate, in great Eſteem with the Emperor, and of ſo great Devotion, that, imbracing our Saviour's Counſel, <hi>he Sold all,</hi> diſtributed it to the Poor, and pious Uſes, and betook himſelf to a ſtrict Religious Life in Poverty, after he had been preferred to great publick Offices; he was a Man of Parts and Learning, and well acquainted with the Weſtern parts, eſpecially <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and for his great Virtues and eminent Sanctity was, by the Importunity of the People, made Biſhop of <hi>Nola</hi> in <hi>Campania:</hi> ſo that he alſo was every way qualified for another Witneſs in this Caſe: and theſe two I ſuppoſe ſufficient for their time, eſpecially for the <hi>Latin</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paulinus</hi> in an Epiſtle to St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays as much as need to be in few Words; that
<note n="*" place="margin">Vacare non poſſe, quòd univerſa pro Defunctis Eccleſia ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evit, <hi>ap Aug. de Cura pro Mort. pr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It cannot be in vain that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church is accuſtomed to pray for the Dead.</hi> Not the <hi>Church,</hi> but the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church; not only did at that time, but was <hi>accuſtomed</hi> ſo to do; that is, time out of mind, without any known beginning. And what was it accuſtomed to do? Not barely to commemorate, but to pray and ſupplicate for them. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſa pro Defunctis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia ſupplicare conſuevit.</hi> As ample a Teſtimony, I think, as can be expreſſed in ſo few words.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in confirmation of this alleadgeth the Book of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees,</hi> and addeth,
<note n="‖" place="margin">Sed etſi nuſquam in Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teribus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no legere<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur, non parva ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eſt Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſae Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, quae. in h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine claret, Authoritas; ubi in pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſace<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quae Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Deo ad ejus altare funduntur, <hi>locum ſuum</hi> habet etiam <hi>Commendatio Mortuorum, S. Aug. de Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pro Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis, c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>But altho' we did no where at all read this in the ancient Writings, yet is not the Authority of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41225:14"/>which is clear in this Cuſtom, a ſmall matter, when in the Prayers of the Priest, which are poured out to the Lord God at his Altar,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration <hi>of the Deceaſed hath alſo its proper place.</hi> In this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony are divers things obſervable, and very conſiderable: 1. The Authority of the Univerſal Church, not of a Particular Church, of a City, of a Province, of <hi>Hippo,</hi> or <hi>Africa,</hi> but of the Univerſal Church, which, however manifeſted or declared, is no ſmall matter. 2. But in this it is declared, in the moſt Solemn Acts of the Church, her moſt Solemn Addreſs to Almighty God at his Altar. So that here is the greateſt Authority that is among Mankind, and that moſt ſolemnly declared. 3. It is no new Reſolution, but a Cuſtom, <hi>Conſuetudo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſae Eccleſiae,</hi> an ancient Cuſtom, and a univerſal Cuſtom, which he elſewhere upon another occaſion expreſſeth in this manner:
<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Univerſa obſervat Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, ut pro eis, qui in Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functi ſunt, cum ad ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium <hi>ſuo loco</hi> commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; pro il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> id offerri com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoretur. <hi>S. Aug. de verb. Apoſt. Ser.</hi> 32. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>This being delivered from the Fathers</hi> (à Patribus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum) <hi>doth the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church obſerve, that for them who are departed in the Communion of the Body and Blood of Christ, when they are remembred at the Sacrifice it ſelf in their place, Prayer be made, and it be commemorated that that is offered for them alſo.</hi> Not only for the Living, but for the Dead alſo, and in their proper place. 4. This Cuſtom and Tradition was not only for a general Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but for a ſpecial Commendation.</p>
            <p>And here, becauſe this excellent Perſon hath written much, and therefore affords more obſervable matter than is ordinary in any one Author, I will indeavour out of him alone to preſent the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ingenuous Reader with <hi>a Scheme of the whole Cuſtom and Practice of the Ancients,</hi> whereby he will the better underſtand their Teſtimonies, and decern the Fallacies, Evaſions, Cavillings and Shufflings of the Adverſaries of it. What was done by them on behalf of the Deceaſed was either Publick or Private: What was done in <hi>Private,</hi> was Prayers, ſuch as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> offered for his Mother in his Confeſſions, <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. Faſting, and Alms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What was <hi>Publick,</hi> was done either <hi>by the Relations or Friends</hi> of the Perſons deceaſed, and that was preſenting their Oblations, whether ordered by the Deceaſed, or freely offered by their Friends on their behalf: Which, if they departed in Communion of the Church were received, otherwiſe rejected, unleſs they were in the State of Penitents, and were ſurprized in ſuch caſe as the Prieſt ſhould have abſolved them, if he could have been preſent: or what was done <hi>by the Biſhop or Priest,</hi> with the reſt of the Clergy and People: And this was either a general Commemoration <hi>pro
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41225:14"/>omnibus in Chriſtiana &amp; Catholica Societate defunctis,</hi> as he ſpeaks <hi>de Cura pro Mat. c.</hi> 4. for all departed in the Chriſtian and Catholick Society, (or Communion) without any particular recitation of their Names, or a more particular Memory of them by Name with others; or a more <hi>ſpecial Commendation</hi> of a particular Perſon at his Death; and, beſides certain other days, upon their Anniverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And theſe were all performed at the Altar, and with the Holy Sacrifice, except that at his Death, in caſe that happened after the Prieſt had eaten, and then by ſome Canons it was to be performed <hi>ſolis Orationibus,</hi> with Prayers only; but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>&amp; Orationibus &amp; Oblationibus;</hi> that is, with Prayers and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice both, for that is there to be underſtood by <hi>Oblationibus.</hi> And as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did intend all this in what he ſaith of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Cuſtom by Tradition from the Fathers, ſo did he believe that the Souls departed were benefitted by them all. For his words immediately preceeding thoſe before-recited out of his <hi>Serm. de Verb. Apoſt.</hi> are,
<note n="*" place="margin">Orationib. vero S. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, &amp; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio ſalutari, &amp; Eleemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynis, quae pro eorum ſpi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantur, non eſt dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos adjurari, ut cum eis miſericordius agatur à Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, quam eorum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> 
               <hi>It is not to be doubted that the Dead are helped by the Prayers of the H. Church, and the Salutary Sacrifice, and the Alms which are diſtributed for their Spirits, that the Lord ſhould deal more mercifully with them than their Sins have deſerved.</hi> This was one End and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe Commemorations and Prayers; and therefore was not only comprehended in the general Intendment of the general Commemorations, but was expreſsly prayed for both in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers and in the more ſpecial Commendations, as we ſhall ſee further hereafter; but this does not exclude <hi>Others;</hi> of which, I think fit to take notice of one in this place, which is mentioned by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and others, and which concern two Articles of our Creed, but little underſtood or conſider'd amongſt us. It is in his Book <hi>de Civ. Dei, lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. in theſe words:
<note n="†" place="margin">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim piorum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, quae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam nunc eſt regnum Chriſti. Alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin nec ad altare Dei fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eret corum memoria: in communione Corporis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Nor are the Souls of the Pious deceaſed ſeparated from the Church, which even now is the Kingdom of Christ: Otherwiſe, neither at the Altar of God ſhould Memory be made of them in the Communion of the Body of Christ.</hi> In theſe words is couched one general Intendment of the Church: For as the Holy Rite of the Euchariſt was intended not only for <hi>the Peculiar Solemnity of the Churches Addreſs to God</hi> here upon Earth, with the Memorials of our Saviour's Paſſion, the great Propitiation for the Sins of the World, but alſo for <hi>Communion</hi> between our Head and the Members of his Myſtical Body here upon Earth, and alſo between the Members of his whole Myſtical Body themſelves; ſo the Church in that Holy Solemnity hath always performed <hi>Acts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41225:15"/>of Communion,</hi> not only with the Head, but with all his Members, both preſent, in external Communion, and <hi>Participation</hi> of the ſanctified Creatures; and with all abſent, whether in the Body, or out of the Body, by <hi>Commemorations,</hi> Thankſgivings and Prayers. And becauſe they were in ſeveral States, they were accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred diſtinctly, in order, which is what S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> expreſſeth <hi>ſuo loco.</hi> This <hi>Communion</hi> was by the ancient Chriſtians reputed a matter of very great Importance, and accordingly they were equally careful, whoſe Oblations they did receive, and whoſe Names they did remember, whether Living or Dead: and thoſe who were ejected, or rejected or refuſed, were looked upon as out of Communion, and excluded from all the Privileges of the Church, both on Earth, and alſo in the ſeparate State, according to our Saviour's Promiſe. It was then believed, that the Souls departed, which ſhould be ſaved, were all indeed with Chriſt, but not at the Right-hand of his Father; but ſome before the Throne; ſome upon <hi>Mount Sion;</hi> ſome in the Holy of Holies; ſome in the Temple, but not in that place; ſome in Paradice, in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom, in the Third Heaven, in very different Manſions or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles: as one may be ſaid to be with the King, who is with him in foreign Parts, tho' but in his Army, or at his Court, tho' never admitted into his Preſence Chamber; and that by ſome the Church here upon Earth her ſelf received much Benefit; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers received Benefit by her Communion and Prayers, and ſtood in need of it. Nor ought we to think that theſe two Articles of <hi>the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> and <hi>the Communion of Saints,</hi> were put into the Summary of the Chriſtian Faith and Profeſſion, and in the Order they are, but for ſpecial and weighty Reaſons; and indeed ſuch as are little taught, or underſtood, or regarded amongſt us in this Age.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> hath many Teſtimonies concerning this matter of Fact and known Practice of the Church in theſe diſtinct Orders of Commemoration of the Dead, ſo plain, that the Arch-Biſhop himſelf could not but confeſs that in <hi>the Church Service there was made a ſeveral Commemoration; first, of the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, and Martyrs, after one manner; and then of the other Dead, after another,</hi> pag. 194. and one or two he cites in the Margin, but was ſo wiſe as not to recite the words. It is <hi>Serm.</hi> 17. <hi>de Verbis Apoſt.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ideò<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na quod fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les noverunt, cum Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res eo loco recitantur ad altare Dei, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi non pro ipſis oretur, pro caeteris autem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoralis defunctis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur. Injuria eſt enim pro Martyre ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, cujus nos debemus ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus com mendari. <hi>And Tr.</hi> 84. <hi>in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. Johan.</hi>
                  </note> This hath the Church Diſcipline, which the Faithful know, when the Martyrs are recited at the Altar of God in that place, where Prayer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41225:15"/>is not made for them; but Prayer is made for others, who are commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. For it is an Injury to pray for a Martyr, to whoſe Prayers we (our ſelves) ought to be commended.</hi> And Tr. 84. in Evang. Johan.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ad ipſam menſam non ſic eos <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoramus,</hi> quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum alior, qui in pace requieſcunt, u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> et<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am pro eis <hi>or mus,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d magis, ut crentipſi pro nobis; ut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giis adhae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus; quia impleverunt ipſi charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, qua Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus dixit non poſſe eſſe majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> 
               <hi>At the Table it ſelf we do not ſo commemorate them, as others who rest in Peace, that we ſhould alſo pray for them, but rather that they pray for us, that we may tread in their Steps; becauſe they themſelves have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled that Charity, than which our Lord ſaith there cannot be greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I cannot but take notice of <hi>the Partiality and Diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity of this magnified Man</hi> in this place; for it is a Scandal and Offence to me. Having cited the words of S. <hi>Auguſtin in Euchrid. ad Laurent.</hi> cap. 110.
<note n="‖" place="margin">Cum ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia ſive alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, five qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumcunque Eleemoſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pro bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis omnibus offeruntur; pro valdè bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum actiones ſunt; pro val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè malis, et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi nulla ſunt adjumenta mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuorum, qua<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolationes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> 
               <hi>That the Oblations and Alms uſually offered in the Church for all the Dead that received Baptiſm, were Thankſgivings for ſuch as were very Good; Propitiations for ſuch as were not very Bad: but for ſuch as were very Evil, altho' they were no Help for the Dead, yet were they ſome kind of Conſolations of the Living.</hi> He calls this <hi>a Private Expoſition;</hi> not only (as he pretends) becauſe it is not to be found in the Writings of the former Fathers; but alſo becauſe it ſuiteth not well with the general Practice of the Church, which it intendeth to interpret, <hi>p.</hi> 194. If it had not been in the Writings of any of the former Fathers, had not the notorious Practice of the Church, which he often mentions with ſpecial notes of the Notoriety of the matter of Fact, been ſufficient, and much more than any thing mentioned dogmatically by others, tho' more ancient? But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that is falſe: for we ſhall ſee it hereafter atteſted by <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> and not by the by, but in a profeſſed Deſcription, and Explication of the <hi>Greek</hi> Liturgy; which ſhews the Agreement of all, both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches. And therefore it is but reaſonable that the honeſt Reader be admoniſhed to beware of this Author, how he truſts him: for he is a partial and crafty Writer; of which other inſtances may be produced.</p>
            <p>But perhaps it may not only do right to S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> but be a Satisfaction to the Reader, to ſee him more fully declare his mind, which he doth in the words precedent, to this effect:
<note n="*" place="margin">Neque negandum eſt Deſu ctorum animas pietate ſuorum viventium relevari, cum pro illis ſacrificium Media<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oris offertur, vel Eleemoſynae in Eccleſia fiunt. Sed e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s haec pro unt qui cum viverent, ut haec ſibi poſtea prodeſſe poſſent, meruerunt. Eſt enim quidem vive<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di modus, nec tam bonus, ut non requirat ifta poſt mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tem; nec tam malus, ut ei non proſint iſta poſt mortem. Eſt vero talis in b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no, ut iſta non requirat; &amp; eſt rurſus talis in malo, ut nec his valeat, oum ex h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vita tranſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, adjuvari. Quo circa hic omne meritum comparatur, quo poſſit poſt h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam releva<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i, quiſplam, vel gravari. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo autem ſe ſperet quod hic neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexerit cum obierit, apud Deum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moreri. Non igitur iſta quae pro de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendandis frequentat Eccleſia, il<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Apoſtolicae ſunt adverſa ſententiae, qua dictum eſt; <hi>Omnes enim aſtabimus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Tribunal Chriſti, utre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerat unuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ea quae per corpus geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ſivebonum, ſive malum:</hi> quia etiam hoc meritum ſibi quiſque cum in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eret comparavit, ut ei poſſent iſta prodeſſe. Non enim omnibus proſunt, &amp; quare non omnibus proſunt, niſipropter differentiam vitae, quam quiſque geſſit in corpore? Cum ergo ſacificia <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nor is it to be denied,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the Souls of the Deceaſed are relieved by the Piety of their living Relations, when the Sacrifice of the Mediator is offered,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41225:16"/>or Alms given in the Church for them. But to thoſe are theſe things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, who, when they lived, merited that theſe things might be profitable for them afterward. For there is one ſort of Life neither ſo Good, that it might not need thoſe things after Death; nor ſo Evil, that they cannot profit after Death. But there is ſuch in Good, that it may not require them: and there is again ſuch in Evil, that it cannot be helped by theſe things when this Life is ended. Wherefore here is all Merit acquired, whereby any one can after this Life be relieved, or grieved. But let none hope that he may obtain of God after he is Dead what he hath neglected here. Wherefore thoſe things, which the Church doth frequently uſe for Recommending the Dead, are not contrary to the Sentence of the Apoſtle, where it is ſaid,</hi> We muſt all ſtand before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive according to thoſe things which he hath done in the Body, whether it be Good, or Evil; <hi>becauſe even this Merit every one acquired for himſelf when he lived in the Body, that theſe things might profit him. For they do not profit all. And why do they not profit all, but by reaſon of the Difference of Life which each lived in the Body? When therefore Sacrifices, whether of the Altar, or of whatever Alms, are offered for all the Deceaſed, who were baptized, &amp;c.</hi> as before recited by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi> More to like purpoſe may be ſeen in his Book <hi>de Cura pro Mortuis,</hi> cap. 4. and cap. 18. where he adds,
<note n="‖" place="margin">Sed quia non diſcernimus qui ſint, oportet ea pro regeneratis omnibus facere, u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nullus eorum praeterm<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tatur, ad quos haec beneficia poſſint &amp; debeant pervenire. Melius enim ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererunt iſta eis, quibus nec obſunt, nec proſunt, quam eis deerunt quibus proſunt. Diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius tamen facit haec quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pro neceſſariis ſuis, quod pro illo fiat ſimiliter à ſuis, <hi>p.</hi> 294. <hi>b.</hi> 2. <hi>to</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>But becauſe we do not diſtinguiſh who they are,</hi> (who are profited by them) <hi>we ought to do theſe things for all the Regenerate, that none of them be pretermitted, to whom theſe Benefits may and ought to come. For it is better that they ſhould be ſuperfluous as to them, who are neither helped nor hurt by them, than be wanting to thoſe whom they may benefit. Yet every one doth theſe things the more diligently for his (deceaſed) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that the ſame may be done by his Relations (ſurviving) for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> The ſame he hath qu. 2. <hi>ad Dulcitium:</hi> and more to like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Serm.</hi> 32. <hi>de Verb. Apoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Teſtimonies of theſe two Eminent, Holy, Learned Biſhops of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, I will add the Teſtimonies of two or three Eminent Biſhops of the ſame Age in the <hi>Greck</hi> Church, concerning the Practice and Cuſtom of the Church in their time, and the Ages
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41225:16"/>precedent, even to the Apoſtles, in this Caſe. The one is S. <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> a Man as eminent for his own perſonal Worth, as for the Place he held. He hath much concerning Prayers and Oblations for the Dead; but much of it by way of Exhortation: and therefore to be as brief as may be, I will ſelect principally what concerns the Practice and Original, which he refers expreſsly to the Ordination of the Apoſtles, and Directions of the Holy Spirit. But firſt for the common Practice of the People: <hi>Hom.</hi> 32. <hi>in Mat.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Why after the Death of any of thy Family doſt thou call the Poor together? Why dost intreat the Presbyters to pray for him?</hi> Thou wilt ſay, <hi>That he may obtain Rest. And doſt thou then weep and lament for theſe things?</hi> Secondly, S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi>'s Advice, <hi>Hom.</hi> 61. <hi>in Johan.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But if a Sinner, and who hath often offended God, dieth, is he to be bewailed? or rather, not at all, ſince that cannot do him any good. But theſe things are to be performed for him, which may do him good;</hi> viz. <hi>Alms and Oblations.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Alms, he preſſeth it much, <hi>Hom.</hi> 21. <hi>in Act.</hi> pag. 605. And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> for the common Office of the Prieſt, in his Sixth Book <hi>de Sacerdotio,</hi> cap. 4.
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>What manner of Man ought he to be, who interceeds for the whole City? What, do I ſay for the City? for the whole World, and prays to God that he will be propitious to the Sins of all, not only of the Living, but alſo of the Dead?</hi> Then that theſe things are of Apoſtolical Authority, <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>in Phil</hi> in the Moral. Exhorting People to pray themſelves, and to intreat the Prayers of others, and to give Alms continually for their deceaſed Friends:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Will this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>give any Relief?</hi> and then anſwers: <hi>Hear God thus ſaying,</hi> I will protect this City for my own and for my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>David</hi>'s ſake. <hi>If the Memory only of a righteous Man avails ſo much, where Works are alſo done for the Dead, what cannot they do?</hi> and then goes on: <hi>Theſe things were not in vain</hi> conſtituted by the Apoſtles, <hi>that in the venerable and tremendous Myſteries Memorial ſhould be made of thoſe who were departed. They knew much Beneſit would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41225:17"/>accure to them by it, and much Advantage. For at that time, when all the People ſtand with their hands lifted up, and the Company of the Prieſts, and that venerable and awful Sacrifice, preſent, how ſhall we not pleaſe or appeaſe God praying for them? And that indeed for thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in the Faith; But the</hi> Catechumens <hi>are not deign'd this Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but are deſtitute of all help, one only excepted. But what is that? Why, Alms may be given to the Poor for them: and hence they receive ſome Refreſhment. For it is God's Will that we ſhould mutually help one another.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Hom.</hi> 69. <hi>ad Pop. Antioch. Laſtly,</hi> and that this was by the Direction of the Holy Spirit, he is expreſs, <hi>Hom.</hi> 21. <hi>in Act.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Not in vain are Oblations for the Dead; Not in vain Prayers; Not in vain Alms: For all theſe things did the</hi> Spirit <hi>Order, willing that we ſhould mutually help one another.... Doubt it not, the Fruit will be pleaſant: It is not a light thing that the Deacon calls out,</hi> (to pray) <hi>For thoſe who are departed in Christ; and, For thoſe who offer for their Memories.</hi> And the ſame he ſaith alſo, <hi>Hom.</hi> 41. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and adds:
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>For if Commemorations were not made for them, not ſo much as this would be ſaid: For our Matters are not Stage-Plays. Far be that. For theſe are done by the</hi> Ordination and Diſpoſition of the Spirit. <hi>Let us therefore afford them help, and perform their Commemorations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Propitiation propoſed is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the World: therefore do we then confidently</hi> pray <hi>for all the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and</hi> name <hi>them with Martyrs, with Confeſſors, with Prieſts: for we are all one Body, tho' ſome Members more ſplendid than others.... Why doſt thou grieve and lament ſo much? Favour may be obtained for the Deceaſed.</hi> And that he himſelf formed a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which is at this day in uſe in the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, is affirmed by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and cannot with any good reaſon be denied; and tho' 'tis likely there may be ſome Alterations or Additions in it, yet what relates to this matter is ſo confirmed by this, and by more ancient Authority, that it cannot reaſonably be queſtioned.</p>
            <p>The other is S. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salamis,</hi> the Metropolis of the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> a Man of good Reputation for Ability and Piety, and particularly ſtudied in all the Doctrines and Practices of the Church, and the ſeveral Hereſies contrary thereunto. In him we have a double Teſtimony, that of <hi>Aerius,</hi> and his own, in a Book of all the Hereticks and Hereſies. In that of <hi>Aerius,</hi> is obſervable,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41225:17"/>1. The Matter of Fact and common Practice, <hi>viz.</hi> commemorating the Names of the Dead, and Praying for them. 2.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The End for which it was done, <hi>viz.</hi> That they might be benefitted by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their Sins at the Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of their Surviving Friends and the Church. Both theſe he oppoſeth; and that is a Proof of both; and by the Teſtimony of an Adverſary; which is reputed the moſt convincing. 3. The Oppoſition, without any denial or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Antiquity or Univerſality of the Practice or Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or of the Tradition of either the Practice, or the Intention and Doctrine: which, if he had had any colour or pretence for it, he would certainly never have omitted: but he is able to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt either the Practice, or Benefit of it; but, If it be ſo, it is in vain to be pious; it would be ſufficient to get People to pray for the Pardon of ones Sins after his Death. In all theſe reſpects is the Oppoſition of <hi>Aerius</hi> a very conſiderable Teſtimony of both the Practice and Intention, and conſequently of the Doctrine of the Church in this caſe. But becauſe our great Man uſeth his utmoſt Skill, and very groſsly, to evade and elude theſe Teſtimonies, I will here preſent them both intire, according to his own Tranſlation, with Notes of the Pages where moſt of the diſtracted Parcels may be found in his Book, that the Reader who hath a mind to entertain himſelf with a Proſpect of his Ingenuity, may the more plainly diſcern it.</p>
            <p>The Objection of <hi>Aerius: For what reaſon do you commemorate after Death, the Names of thoſe that are departed? He that is alive prayeth, or maketh Diſpenſation</hi> (of the Myſteries) <hi>what ſhall the Dead be profited hereby? And if the Prayer of thoſe here do</hi> altogether (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>profit them that be there; then let no body be Godly;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> let no Man do Good; but let him procure ſome Friends, by what means it pleaſeth him, either by perſuading them by Money, or intreating Friends at his Death; and let them pray for him, that he may ſuffer nothing there; and that thoſe inexpiable Sins, which he hath committed, may not be required at his hands.</hi> p. 238.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his Anſwer and Teſtimony: <hi>As for the reciting of the Names of thoſe that are deceaſed, what can be better than this? What more commodious, and more admirable? that ſuch as are preſent do</hi> believe <hi>that they who are departed do live, and are not extinguiſhed, but are ſtill Being, and Living with the Lord: and that this most pious Preaching
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41225:18"/>might be declared, that they who pray for their Brethren have</hi> hope <hi>of them, as being in a Peregrination,</hi> p. 240. <hi>But the Prayer alſo which is made for them doth profit, altho' it doth not cut off</hi> All <hi>their Sins.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here anſwers to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Objection.) <hi>Yet, foraſmuch as whilſt we are in the World, we oftentimes ſlip both unwillingly, and with our Will; it ſerveth to ſignifie that which is more perfect: For we make a Memorial, both of the Just, and for Sinners: For Sinners, intreating the Mercy of God; of the Just, both the Fathers, and Patriarchs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts, and Martyrs, and Confeſſors, Biſhops, and Anchoretes, and the whole Order; that we may ſever our Lord Jeſus from the Rank of all other Men, by the Honour that we do vnto him, and that we may yield Worſhip unto him, [while we thus judge,</hi> p. 240. <hi>That] our Lord is not to be compared unto any Man; tho' a Man live in Righteouſneſs a thouſand times and more: for how ſhould that be poſſible? conſidering that the one is God, the other Man; and the one is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the other in Earth, by reaſon of the Remains (or Reliques) of the Body yet reſting in the Earth.</hi> [p. 242. <hi>Except thoſe, who being raiſed from the Dead, entred together into the Bride-Chamber, as ſaith the Holy Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But forbearing theſe things, I return to what I was about.] The Church doth neceſſarily perform this, having received it by</hi> Tradition <hi>from the Fathers: And who may diſſolve the Ordinances of his Mother, or the Law of his Father?</hi> p. 237. [<hi>as</hi> Solomon <hi>ſaith,</hi> Hear, my Son, the Words of thy Father, and reject not the Laws of thy Mother; <hi>declaring by this, that (our) Father; that is, God, the Only begotten, and the Holy Spirit, hath taught (us) both in Scriptures, and without Scripture: But] our Mother, the Church, hath Ordinances ſettled in her, which are inviolable, and may not be broken. Seeing then there are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances eſtabliſhed in the Church, and they are well, and all things are admirably done; this Seducer is again refuted.</hi> p. 237. This is the Anſwer of <hi>Epiphanius:</hi> the words inclos'd in Crochets are not in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41225:18"/>
            <p> To this we may well apply what he ſaith before concerning <hi>Eaſter,</hi> the Obſervation of which was another thing, which <hi>Aerius</hi> quarrelled at: <hi>But who knows theſe things beſt? This ſeduced Fellow, who is but newly ſprung up, and now living amongst us; or they who were Witneſſes before us; and who held the ſame Tradition in the Church before us, which they had received from their Parents, and their Parents had learned from their Anceſtors; as the Church to this day obſerves the true and ſincere Faith, which it received with the Traditions from the Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all this we may obſerve, 1. The Practice of the Church, both in the General Commemorations, and in the Prayers, agreed on both Sides. 2. The End and Intendment of the Church, that it was the Profit and Benefit of the Deceaſed, alſo agreed. 3. The Queſtion between them, Whether the Prayer of the Living could profit or benefit the Dead, as the Church intended? 4. That this was what <hi>Aerius</hi> did principally deny: and therefore, that the Practice was reaſonable, as a neceſſary conſequence. 5. His only reaſon was, that it would make Piety and good Life needleſs. 6. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his Anſwer, 1. from Reaſon; 1. as it is a ſeaſonable and excellent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claraction of the Faith and Hope of the Church; 2. as an Act of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for the Benefit of the Deceaſed; 2. from Authority, as received in the Church by Tradition from our Saviour, and the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>And now, how does our great Man elude this? <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> ſaith he, doth not <hi>Name</hi> this, (<hi>viz.</hi> That Prayers and Sacrifice profiteth not the depa ted in Chriſt,) an Hereſie. 2. Nor doth it appear that himſelf did hold that they bring <hi>ſuch Profit</hi> to the Dead as theſe Men Dream, <hi>pag.</hi> 236. 3. He doth not at all charge him with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Doctrine of the Scripture, or the Faith of the Catholick Church, but with rejecting the Order, <hi>p.</hi> 237. 4. <hi>Aerius</hi> his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would have been in force indeed, if the whole Church had held, as many did; <hi>That the Judgment after Death was ſuſpended until the General Reſurrection, and that in the mean time, the Sins of the Dead might be taken away by the Suffrages of the Living:</hi> But he ſhould have conſidered, as <hi>Gobarus</hi> (as great an Heretick as himſelf) did that the <hi>Doctors</hi> were not agreed upon the Point, <hi>p.</hi> 238.5. It was a fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh part in him to confound the <hi>Private Opinion</hi> of ſome, with the <hi>Common Faith</hi> of the Univerſal Church. 6. That he reproved this <hi>particular Error,</hi> he did well; but that thereupon he condemned the <hi>General Practice</hi> of the Church, he did like himſelf, headily and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly, <hi>ibidem.</hi> As to the firſt of theſe, I muſt refer the Reader to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41225:19"/>
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> himſelf, for the Character he gives of the Perſon and Opinions of <hi>Aerius,</hi> a very Vile man, a thorough-pac'd <hi>Arian,</hi> and who exceeded <hi>Arius</hi> himſelf in his new Opinions, which he imputes to the operation of the Devil; though he doth not particularly <hi>name</hi> them Hereſies, yet, it is plain, he and S <hi>Auſtin</hi> too accounted them ſuch; and, of the reſt, the Reader may judge by what is here laid plainly before him.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Ephraem</hi> was not much before theſe; but becauſe he was neither <hi>Greek</hi> nor <hi>Latin,</hi> but a <hi>Syrian,</hi> and a Man of Parts and extraordinary Sanctity, greatly eſteemed by the moſt excellent Perſons of that time, and of ſo great Reputation, that his Writings were read publickly in divers Churches after the Holy Scriptures, I cannot paſs him by without taking notice of his Teſtament, his Diſcourſe to his Diſciples upon his Death-Bed: wherein he tells them he is Dying, and deſires to be mentioned in the Commemoration of their Holy Prayers; and bewailing his Sins, and declaring his Senſe of the terrible Judgment of God, he doth admoniſh, exhort, and ſtrictly enjoyn them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him conſtantly, <hi>after his exit and paſſage,</hi> in their Prayers: and after ſome Admonitions to them, and account of himſelf, he again deſires to be remembred in their Prayers. Then he ſtrictly forbids his being Buried under the Altar, or in the Houſe of God, all Solemn Pomp, and Funeral Orations and Encomiums; and all coſt of rich Veſtments, of Grave Cloaths, of Spices, of Odors, of Candles, and the like; but deſires that all that Coſt may be beſtowed upon the Poor; and for himſelf; that in the place of all ſuch Pomp and Funeral Orations, they will accompany him with Pſalms, and help and aſſiſt him with their Prayers, and Bury him in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, where the contrite in heart are Buried. Then he bids them come near and imbrace him, for his Spirit fails him, and again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats them diligently to make Oblations for him; and prettily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> by a Simile of the Sympathy of things in Nature, the Wine which flowers in the Cellar, when the Vine Buds in the Vineyard, and the like: And tells them, that the Oblations of Prieſts under the Law were effectual for thoſe who were ſlain in their Sins: and how much more the Prieſts of Chriſt under the New Teſtament! And gives great caution, that when they come to his Memory, (I ſuppoſe he means the Thirtieth Day, which he expreſsly mentioned before and his Anniverſaries) <hi>ne quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in Sancta peccet;</hi> that none commit any thing unmeet for holy things, (by any Exceſs): but that the Vigil be kept atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41225:19"/>and reverently, and humbly, and holily, and purely: for it would be a miſerable thing for him, if by occaſion of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, he ſhould be accountable to his God for their inordinate Actions. Thus this Holy Man: an Inſtance equal to a very ample Teſtimony of the Practice in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time was S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> He in his <hi>Myſtagogick Catechiſm</hi> concludes all with a Deſcription and Scheme of the Liturgy then in uſe; wherein, after mention of the Holy <hi>Triſagium</hi> Hymn,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do we recite this Seraphick Theology delivered to us, that in that Coeleſtial Hymnody we may communicate with the</hi> ſupra-mundain Militia, <hi>(the Heavenly Host:) and thus by ſuch kind of Hymns ſanctiſying our ſelves, we pray the most benign God that he will ſend out his Holy Spirit upon the propoſited (Elements) that it may make the Bread the Body of Christ, and the Wine the Blood of Christ. For certainly, whatever the Holy Spirit doth touch, it is ſanctified and tranſmuted. Then after that Spiritual Sacrifice, that unbloody Worſhip is done,</hi> (that is, after the Conſecration and Oblation in Commemoration of the Paſſion of Chriſt) <hi>over that very Host of Propitiation do we obſecrate God for the common Peace of the Churches; for the Tranquility of the World; for Kings; for their Armies and Confederates; for the Sick and Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; and, in ſum, for all who need Help. We commemorate alſo thoſe who have fallen aſleep before us: Firſt, the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, that God at their Prayers and Deprecations would accept ours: Then</hi> we pray <hi>for the Holy Fathers and Biſhops deceaſed; and,</hi> laſtly, <hi>for all who are deceaſed amongst us, believing it to be a very great Help to the Souls, for whom the Obſecration of that tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Sacrifice, which is placed on the Altar, is offered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will add but one inſtance more for the flouriſhing times of the Church, and ſo comprize the whole time of the four firſt General Councils from firſt to laſt. <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his 4th Book of the Life of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> deſcribing the <hi>Martyrium</hi> of the Apoſtles, built by him at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> adds, chap. 60. <q>All theſe did the Emperor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41225:20"/>dedicate, that he might conſign to Poſterity the Memory of our Saviour's Apoſtles. But he had another Deſign in his Mind when he built this Church: which was at firſt concealed: but in the end it became known to all. For he had deſigned this place for himſelf after his Death, foreſeeing, by a tranſcendent Alacrity of Faith, that his Body after Death ſhould be made <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Apoſtles Apellation,</hi> that even <hi>after Death,</hi> he might be <hi>eſteemed worthy of the Prayers,</hi> which ſhould be performed there in Honour of the Apoſtles, believing that their Memory would be <hi>uſeful and advantagious to his Soul.</hi>
               </q> And afterward deſcribing the Solemnity of his Funeral, <hi>chap.</hi> 71. he ſaith, that <q>
                  <hi>a vaſt Number</hi> of People, together with thoſe Perſons, conſecrated to God, not without Tears and great Lamentation, <hi>poured forth Prayers to God for the Emperor's Soul;</hi> thereby performing a moſt grateful Office to this pious Prince. And herein alſo God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated his ſingular Favour towards his Servant, becauſe after his Death, — agreeable to <hi>his own moſt earneſt Deſire,</hi> the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of his thrice bleſſed Soul was vouchſafed a place with the Monument of the Apoſtles; and that it might be joined with God's People in the Church; and might be vouchſafed the Divine Rights, and Myſtick Service; and might <hi>enjoy a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Holy Prayers.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This was but 12 years after the <hi>Nicen</hi> Council, and a great and moſt illuſtrious inſtance of the common received and ſettled Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of that time. And here, before I proceed further, it is fit to conſider, how far the continuance of that wicked and ſhameful Abuſe by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> put upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> in his clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine Corruption of the <hi>True Engliſh Liturgy;</hi> I ſay, the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of it to this day, whether by ſupine Negligence, or baſe Compliance with a Faction of Sectaries, be conſiſtent with that Profeſſion of Reverence to Antiquity in general; and to thoſe firſt four General Councils in particular, which is made by all who pretend to be genuine Sons of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> with their uſe of the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan Creed</hi> in the moſt ſolemn Office, ſo fouly deformed, contrary to the Publick Office at that time uſed in the Church, and atteſted by S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> who was preſent at that Council, and a principal Man there? How conſiſtent with the Statutes of moſt ancient Colleges in both the Univerſities, and the Oaths taken by ſo many Scholars for the Obſervance of them? How conſiſtent with the Belief of One
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41225:20"/>Holy Catholick Church; and of the Communion of Saints? with that Reverence and Reſpect, which the Holy Scriptures require ſhould be paid to the Body of Chriſt, the Depoſitory of Chriſtian Verities, and the Pillar or Monument and Baſis of Truth? with that Reverence, and Honour, and Eſteem, which all true and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Chriſtians cannot but have for ſo many glorious Saints as flouriſhed in the Church of Chriſt, and all agreed in this pious Practice for more than 1200 years from the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who himſelf was none of the leaſt, being converted in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner by ſpecial Viſion from our Saviour, and the Truth thereof confirmed by very remarkable Victories, and afterward ſo great a Promoter of Chriſtian Piety, that he was, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, partaker of the Apoſtles appellation, being called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Offices of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and deſervedly: How it can be conſiſtent therewith, and with Chriſtian Modeſty, to ſet up a <hi>Calvin,</hi> a <hi>Bucer,</hi> a <hi>Cranmer,</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> like little Idols, above all; and not rather an undeniable proof of the very Spirit of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks.</p>
            <p>Mr.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Life Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix,</hi> p. 55.</note> 
               <hi>Baxter's Queſtions</hi> in another Caſe, not unlike this, may very properly be propoſed to our modern Oppoſers of this Catholick Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: <hi>Would they have held Communion with the Catholick Church for a Thouſand Years together? Or would they not, if they had lived in thoſe times? If they would, then why not with us, who are of the ſame Judgment? Was it a Duty then? And is it unlawful now? If they would not in all thoſe Ages have held Communion with the viſible Church, what would they have done but ſeparated from the Body, and ſo from the Head, and caſt off Chriſt in all his Members, and taken him to be a Head without a Body, which is no Head; and ſo no Christ? What would they have done, but denied his Power, and Love, and Truth, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently his Redemption; and his Office? Hath he come at the end of</hi> 4000 <hi>years ſince the Creation, to redeem the World, that lay ſo long in Darkneſs? And hath he made ſuch wonderful Preparations for his Church, by his Life and Miracles, and Blood and Spirit?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and promiſed, That</hi> the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it; <hi>and that</hi> his Kingdom ſhall be an Everlaſting Kingdom, and his Dominion endureth from Generation to Generation; <hi>and yet, after all this, ſhall he have a Church, (even as the Seekers ſay) but for an Age or two?</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and very good: but if this be good in the Caſe of <hi>Baptiſm of Infants,</hi> why not as good in the Caſe of <hi>Prayers and Oblations for the Dead?</hi> which, I think, hath as good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41225:21"/>Evidence of Apoſtolical Original as that, or the Lord's-Day, or Epiſcopacy, or a good part of the Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And if they ſtand all upon the ſame Foundation, why ſhould they not ſtand or fall together?</p>
            <p>There is alſo <hi>an Aſſertion of St.</hi> Auguſtin<hi>'s,</hi> which deſerves to be here conſidered in this Caſe; That
<note n="*" place="margin">Quod uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa tenet Eccleſia, nec in Conſil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s inſtitutum, ſed ſemper retentum eſt, non niſi Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolica tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum rectiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>cont. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>what the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church doth hold, and was not inſtituted in Councils, but always retained, is most rightly believed to have been delivered by no other than Apoſtolical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> For as this is a Practice which none did ever pretend was inſtituted by any Council; ſo amongſt all, who have written con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Original, or firſt Invention, or Introduction of things, none has ever aſſigned any Original of it in the Catholick Church later than the Apoſtles; or in any part of the Catholick Church, later than of the reſt of Chriſtianity it ſelf. So that could we trace it no further back than the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> it would be unreaſonable to believe, that the whole Chriſtian Church, ſo largely ſpread over the Face of the Earth, and planted by ſo many ſeveral Perſons at firſt, and in Places ſo divided and remote one from another, ſhould ſo unanimouſly agree in ſuch a Practice, did it not proceed from ſome <hi>Common Cauſe;</hi> which could be no other than the <hi>Mutual Agreement</hi> of all the Apoſtles in it.
<note n="*" place="margin">Noſtra qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Scripta cur ignibus meruerunt dari? Cur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticula di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rui? in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Summus oratur Deus, Pax cunctis &amp; venia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulatur, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratibus, Exercitibus, Regibus, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaribus, Inimicis, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc vitam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus, &amp; reſolutis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ſuo. fi.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' this might be ſufficient, yet have we <hi>further Evidence</hi> to trace it, even through the more troubleſome times of the Churches, ſo near to the Apoſtles, that no Man, without Diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to his Judgment, or his Honeſty, can queſtion its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal to be indeed Apoſtolical. For tho' thoſe troubleſome times have left us ſo few Monuments of the Primitive Chriſtianity, in compariſon, that all will hardly equal the Writings of ſome one of the Writers of after-Ages; yet among thoſe few have we what is ſufficient. <hi>Arnobius,</hi> an eminent Profeſſor of Rhetorick, who had been a bitter Enemy againſt the Chriſtians, even in the time of Perſecution under <hi>Diocleſian</hi> turned Chriſtian, and wrote Seven Books againſt the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> in the fourth of which he expoſtulates with them in this manner: <hi>Why have our Scriptures deſerved to be caſt into the Fire? Why our Meeting-Places to be cruelly deſtroyed, in which the Great God is prayed to, Peace and Pardon is beſought for all; for Magiſtrates, Armies, Kings, our Familiars and Enemies; for thoſe yet living, and thoſe releaſed from the Bond of their Bodies?</hi> Where he ſpeaks of Prayers for theſe laſt, as as common as for any of the reſt. About 50 years before this was S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:41225:21"/>a Perſon of great Worth, and moſt deſerved Reputation in the Church, and at laſt a Holy Martyr. He in his LXVI Epiſtle (with his Collegues in Council) tells the Clergy and People, to whom he wrote, that their Predeceſſors, upon religious Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as a neceſſary Proviſion, had decreed, That no Chriſtian Brother at his Departure ſhould name a Clergy-Man for Guardian, or Executor; and that if any one ſhould do this, there ſhould be
<note n="*" place="margin">Si quis hoc feciſſet, non offeretur pro <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, nec ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium pro Do<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitione ejas celebre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Neque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>no Offering for him, nor Sacrifice celebrated for his Departure; for he doth not deſerve to be named at the Altar of God in the Prayer of the Prieſts, who would call away the Prieſts and Miniſters from the Altar:</hi> And therefore ſince one Victor,
<note n="†" place="margin">Contra for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam nuper in Concilio à ſacerdotibus datam.</note> 
               <hi>contrary to the Order lately made in Council by the Prieſts,</hi> had preſumed to conſtitute a certain Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter for a Guardian,
<note n="‖" place="margin">Non eſt quod pro Dormitione ejas apud vos fiat Oblatio, aut Depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio aliqua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ejus in Eccleſia fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentetur.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhould no Oblation be made among them for his Departure, or any Deprecation commonly uſed in the Church in his Name, that the Decree of the Biſhops religiouſly and neceſſarily made might be obſerved by them, and Example given to others,</hi> &amp;c. This Prohibition of thoſe things to be done, by way of Puniſhment, is a plain Evidence of what was accuſtomed, and ſhould have been done, if there had been no Prohibition: and an Evidence not of a ſingle Perſon, but of a Council: and not of Matter of Opinion, but of plain Matter of Fact; and that ſo notorious, as was well known to all, and of ſuch Importance in the Opinion of all, as the Prohibition was adjudged a competent Puniſhment for ſuch a Crime, as they all thought no little one: It was a kind of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>Another fifty years before this lived <hi>Tertullian,</hi> a Man of very great and univerſal Learning, very acute Parts, and very ſtrict for Diſcipline, and for the Orders of the Church. He mentions this Practice in divers of his Writings, not only as common and uſual, but alſo as delivered by Tradition, and ſo well known, and unqueſtionable, as to be it ſelf an undeniable Inſtance and Proof of unwritten Traditions. This he doth in his Book <hi>de Corona Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis,</hi> § 3. where, amongſt the Inſtances which he alleadgeth for proof of the Authority of unwritten Traditions, this is one: <hi>Oblationes pro Defunctis, pro Natalitiis, annua die facimus.</hi> We make Oblations for the Dead upon the Annual day of their Departure; which the Ancient Chriſtians called their <hi>Natalitiae,</hi> or Birth-Days. And after all concludes,
<note n="*" place="margin">Harum &amp; aliarum ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piinarum ſi Legem expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtules Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturarum, nullam inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio tibi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrix, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatrix, &amp; Fides obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatrix.</note> 
               <hi>If of theſe, and other Matters of Diſcipline, you ſeek for a Rule of Scriptures, you ſhall find none: Tradition is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged for the Author, Cuſtom for the Confirmer, and Faith for the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41225:22"/>Obſerver.</hi> But of Traditions in general he hath other Diſcourſes elſewhere: and of this particular Tradition, which he does but only mention here, as an inſtance of Fact not to be denied, we have farther mention in other of his Writings; In his Book <hi>de Monogamia,</hi> againſt ſecond Marriages, ſpeaking of the Cuſtom of the Widow's praying for her deceaſed Husband; he ſays,
<note n="*" place="margin">Et pro ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ejus orat, &amp; Refrigeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um interim adpoſtulat ei, &amp; in prima Reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Conſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; &amp; offert annuis diebus dormitionis ejus. § 10.</note> 
               <q>She prays for his Soul, and intreats for Refreſhment for him in the interim, and Conſort in the firſt Reſurrection, and offers (for him) on the Annual days of his Departure.</q> Again, in his Book <hi>de Exhortatione Caſtitatis,</hi> he thus upbraids him who had had ſeveral Wives:
<note n="†" place="margin">Et jam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pete apud Deum pro cujus Spiritu poſtules, pro qua Oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Annuas reddas. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ergo ad Deum cum tot Uxoribus, quot illa o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoras? &amp; offeres pro duabus, &amp; commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras illas duas per ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogamia ob priſtinum de virginitate ſanctitum, circumda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; univi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? &amp; aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tuum ii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera fronte? &amp; inter cete ras volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes bonae mentis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulabis tibi, &amp; uxori ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiatem<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> § 11</note> 
               <q>Say before God for whoſe Spirit thou doſt pray, for which thou doſt make thy Annual Oblations. Wilt thou therefore ſtand before God with ſo many Wives, as thou doſt in that Prayer remember; and offer for two, and comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate thoſe two by a Prieſt once married, by reaſon of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Sanction of Virginity, incompaſſed with Virgins, and once married Women? And will thy Sacrifice aſcend with Confidence? and amongſt other Habits of a good Soul, wilt thou pray for Chaſtity for thy ſelf, and thy Wife?</q>
            </p>
            <p>This, I think, is plain, and full for the common Practice, both in private, and in publick by the Prieſt at the Altar; and for the Tradition. But it is <hi>objected,</hi> that <hi>Tertullian,</hi> when he wrote theſe Books, was a <hi>Montaniſt,</hi> and wrote them againſt the Church. And it is as eaſily <hi>anſwered,</hi> that it is not Matter of Opinion, but Matter of Fact, for which they are here alleadged: and it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain he was no Fool; which he muſt have been, if this had been the Practice of the <hi>Montaniſts,</hi> and not of the Church. But for the Readers better Information, and more ample Satisfaction, that the Objection is a meer Scarecrow, and ſerves only to diſcover the Diſingenuity and Inconſiderateneſs of the Objectors, he muſt know, <q>That <hi>Montanus,</hi> (and his Companions) <hi>Alcibiades</hi> and <hi>Theodotus,</hi> were at firſt looked upon, in the Opinion of <hi>moſt</hi> Men, as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> For very many Miracles of Divine Grace at that time wrought in many Churches made moſt Men believe that they alſo were Prophets.</q> 
               <hi>Euſeb.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> 3. So that if <hi>Tertullian</hi> did believe this, it was no more than what <hi>moſt</hi> others did. But what more ſpecially inclined him to favour <hi>Montanus</hi> was this: He was a Man of great Auſterity and Strictneſs in Matters of Diſcipline, Penance, Faſting, Chaſtity, Suffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were things which <hi>Montanus</hi> aſſerted, and highly pretended to: And that which fixed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41225:22"/>him in his Opinion of <hi>Montanus,</hi> was ſome unhappy Conteſts which aroſe between him and the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, about ſome of theſe things, which gave him that Offence, that he not only reflects upon them in his <hi>de Corona Militis; Novi &amp; Paſtores eorum,</hi> &amp;c. but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in his other Writings frequently calls them <hi>Pſychici,</hi> Animal or Senſual Man. And this, which is obſervable in his Writings, is alſo affirmed by S. <hi>Hierom.</hi> This was his
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>For as to what relates to the Rule of Faith that is, to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. <hi>and the first Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts were of the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaith</hi> Du Pin p. 82, 83.</note> 
               <hi>Montaniſm.</hi> And what is this to the Prejudice of his Teſtimony concerning Prayers for the Dead? It is ſo far from that, that it is the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and Amplification of it, that this Practice and Tradition was no part of Montaniſm: for nothing could have been a greater Prejudice to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt it, and it had certainly been condemned by them: nor peculiar to the <hi>African</hi> Church; but the known Practice of the Catholick Church, and of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in particular: quite contrary to what the Objectors would perſuade us. But ſuch <hi>Infatuations</hi> are the greateſt of Men ſubject to, when they will obſtinately perſiſt in the Maintenance of an ill Cauſe. We may here therefore fix, upon as good ground as can reaſonably be deſired, this Practice and Tradition of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</p>
            <p>And now it is time to conſider how much we are ſhort in our Evidence of the Apoſtles Age; and from what Original this Practice did in truth proceed. It is agreed that St. <hi>John</hi> wrote his <hi>Goſpel</hi> about the beginning of the ſecond Century; and that <hi>Tertullian</hi> fell to the Sect of <hi>Montanus</hi> in the beginning of the third. <hi>Vid. Du Pin,</hi> p. 44. <hi>and</hi> p. 70. And S. <hi>Hierom</hi> informs us, that he lived to a great Age, <hi>uſque ad decrepitam atatem;</hi> and that after he had continued <hi>uſque ad mediam aetatem</hi> a Presbyter of the Church, <hi>invidia poſtea &amp; contumeliis Clericor. Romanae Eccleſiae ad Montani dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma delapſus.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>After hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued in the Church</hi> 40 <hi>or</hi> 45 <hi>Years, he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from it in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the</hi> 3d <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaith</hi> Du Pin, p. 70.</note> So that he lived the greateſt and beſt part of his Life in the ſame Age wherein St. <hi>John</hi> wrote his Goſpel, and did live ſome time. And here comes, as ſeaſonably as unexpectedly, to my hand, at the very inſtant that this is at the Preſs, a Book of a learned Opponent; who ſeeing this too plain to be diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſuppoſing that he can otherwiſe evade the force of this Evidence, preſents us with a plain Confeſſion of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact;
<note n="†" place="margin">Of the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byls,</hi> l. 2. c 23.</note> 
               <hi>David Blondell:</hi> 
               <q>I make no difficulty (ſaith he) to affirm, that it might be practiſed <hi>ſome time before the Year</hi> 200, in as much as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the moſt ancient of all thoſe that ſay any thing of it, numbred it even then among the <hi>Cuſtoms
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41225:23"/>received</hi> in his time, writing in the Year, 199.</q> 
               <hi>Oblationes pro Defunctis, pro Natalitiis, annua die facimus,</hi> &amp;c. and recites alſo the other two Teſtimonies, only in that <hi>de Monogamia,</hi> miſtakes the Husband for the Wife, and then adds: <q>From the things which this <hi>great Perſon,</hi> the <hi>most Ancient,</hi> and <hi>most Learned</hi> of all the <hi>Latines,</hi> that we have remaining, does advance, as to Matter of Fact, concerning the Oblations, which were publickly made, and the Employment of the Prieſts, the only Miniſters of the publick Service, as a thing <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and <hi>grown into Cuſtom,</hi> it is <hi>manifeſt,</hi> that Praying for the Dead was, in his Time, uſed, not only by particular Perſons, but alſo in the Body of the Church, and that the Liturgies thereof were full of it.</q> Thus we ſee, not only by plain Proof, but alſo by the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The ſame is confeſſed by <hi>John Dalle,</hi> ſince recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to me, as one who hath written learnedly on this Subject: but I find not any thing in him added to</hi> Blendel, <hi>but ſuch Pride, Arrogance, Inſolence, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſimso<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Anci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt Holy Chriſtians &amp; Martyrs, as cannot but be very offenſive to any true Chriſtian Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit being moſt apparently the common Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and obſts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, leading to Atheiſm and Ap ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cy, and as contra ry to the Pare Word of God, which they pretend, as to the true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anty.</hi>
               </note> Confeſſion of a learned Adverſary, that this was not only a <hi>Practice</hi> in the Church when <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote, but a <hi>Received Cuſtom</hi> in his time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ſome ſtanding before; and of ſuch ſtanding as he knew no other Original of it but Apoſtolical Tradition: and for ſuch doth he alleadge it; and not only ſo, but for an unqueſtionable Proof of ſuch unwritten Traditions; as this Author alſo confeſſeth and aſſerts. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 142. And what other Original could it have in that little time, and ſuch a Man as he have been ignorant of it? And had any other been known, could He have been guilty of ſo great Weakneſs, as to have alleadged this for an unqueſtionable Proof in ſuch a Caſe, if he had had ſo little Honeſty?</p>
            <p>But we have here a learned Man, who under pretence of detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Impoſture, preſumes, by his Learning, to impoſe upon the World. How well he hath uſed his Learning in other Matters, ſome Learned Men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I think, beſides others, have ſufficiently ſhewed; and how far his Judgment is to be relied upon. In this I ſhall ſhew the like in a word. He would perſwade that not only <hi>Tertullian,</hi> but the whole Church of Chriſt, hath been impoſed upon in this Matter by a counterfeit <hi>Sibyl,</hi> written between the Years 138 and 151. and of <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith poſitively, <q>That he relied upon no other Hypotheſis than thoſe propoſed by the Author of the pretended <hi>Sibylline</hi> Writings.</q> But in theſe few words there is no leſs than at leaſt one notorious Fallacy, and two Falſities: a Fallacy in the word <hi>Hypotheſis:</hi> for he relied not upon any Hypotheſis, but upon the received Cuſtom of the Church: And that he did rely upon, as is confeſſed: But he did not in the leaſt rely upon any thing at all of the pretended <hi>Sibyl:</hi> Nor hath this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41225:23"/>Champion produced, I think, any one Proof that either <hi>Tertullian,</hi> or any other of the Ancient or Modern Chriſtians, did at all rely upon any ſuch Authority for that Practice: but all unanimouſly relied upon Tradition from the Apoſtles. His whole Book is full of Fallacy and Deceit, and of the very Spirit and Genius of an Heretick, who makes no ſcruple to abuſe the whole Church of Chriſt, and the moſt Excellent Perſons in it, to maintain his own Principles. It is certain, that divers of the great Truths of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity were known to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> long before, and received by Tradition from the Common Parents of Mankind; but received as Articles of Faith by Chriſtians upon the Authority of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: And ſuch was this, which he fathers upon an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and pretends the Church received it from him; without any Proof of either, whereas, if he was a Chriſtian, it is much more likely that he received the Hypotheſis from the Practice of the Church at that time; and is therefore rather an Evidence of it. Other matters of this Book have been conſidered by learned Men of our own Country; and I think I need ſay no more of this with any regard to him.</p>
            <p>But as to the Practice, beſides all this <hi>poſitive and Affirmative Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> I do deny that any competent Evidence can be produced, among all the Churches of the World, of any where the Chriſtian Religion was planted without it, or where it was introduced by any particular Perſon, upon any ſpecial Occaſion, at any different time, after the firſt planting of Chriſtianity there, in all thoſe Ages ſince the Apoſtles; being verily perſuaded that no ſuch thing can be produced, but what will ſtrongly confirm and illuſtate the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Evidence; like Mr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s <hi>Flouriſh</hi> with his moſt ancient Manuſcript <hi>Miſſals,</hi> wherein the Commemoration of the Dead doth no where appear, which yet were but two in all, if not all but one mentioned by two ſeveral Authors, and that no compleat Miſſal nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only <hi>Liber Sacramentorum,</hi> an Abſtract, and it ſelf at laſt not to be found, as his expreſſion, <hi>habebatur,</hi> ſeems to imply: a good Argument of the Agreement of all, or moſt others in that particular, that ſo induſtrious a Searcher into ancient Records and Monuments of Antiquity, of that kind eſpecially, could neither ſee nor hear of any other, either at home or abroad, wherein it was not. Such another Exception may perhaps be met with, which may ſerve to confirm the general Rule; but not any thing conſiderable, I believe, to any other purpoſe. Certain it is, it muſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41225:24"/>either have been ſettled in all thoſe ſeveral Places in the World, where Churches were planted, together with the reſt of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrines and Inſtitutions; and then it muſt have proceeded from the ſame Founders, who agreed as unanimouſly in this, as they did in other neceſſary things; of which ſort this may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be concluded to be one: or it muſt have had a ſeveral diſtinct particular Introduction by it ſelf, in all or moſt of thoſe ſeveral Places, and be derived from ſeveral Authors, Originals, Occaſions and Times: and then the Accounts of its ſpecial and particular Introduction, in all probability, would have very much varied in ſeveral places, at leaſt have remained upon Record, or by Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome. But not a word of any ſuch thing, can I find, that was ever heard of in any part of the World; but a Unanimous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in all, both in the Practice continued by Cuſtom, and Original by Tradition from the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And thus much for Proof <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> from Evidence of Matter of Fact; which I think enough to ſatisfie any reaſonable Man of competent Ability, and to convince any Man of Modeſty and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity: yet becauſe ſimple genuine <hi>Truth</hi> is always conſiſtent with all that is ſuch, it may, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> gratifie an honeſt ingenuous Reader to obſerve briefly the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Agreement</hi> of this Catholick Practice of the Church of Chriſt, 1. With common Reaſon, and the Nature of things: 2. With the common Sentiments of the Primitive Chriſtians concerning the middle State of Souls: 3. With divers plain Texts of the Holy Scriptures: And 4. with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Practice of the <hi>Jews</hi> in and before our Saviour's time, never reprehended by him, or any of his Apoſtles, and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all, and indeed practiſed by them: and, on the contrary, the Inconſiſtence of the obſtinate Oppoſition with Truth and Juſtice in divers reſpects.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Common Reaſon:</hi> The Univerſe is of vaſt and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable extent; in it we ſee are many great Bodies, Orbs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; the Life of Man upon this of the Earth is very ſhort; the Time from the Reſurrection of our Saviour to this is near 1700 years, and how much more it may be to the General Judgment no Mortal knows; in the mean time the Souls of Mortals go out of their Bodies in infinitely various States of Purity and Impurity: And certainly it is moſt reaſonable that there ſhould be, not only one general Diſtinction of Souls, but moreover many diſtinct Places, States, and Conditions, wherein the ſeparate Souls are diſpoſed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41225:24"/>according to their ſeveral Qualifications, when they go out of the Body. And as that curious Obſerver of the Works of Nature, as well of the Holy Scriptures, the late Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hale,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of towardly Plants by Death tranſplanted into another Region, a Garden of Happineſs and Comfort, adds: <q>And poſſibly by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of time, as they received Improvement and Perfection here, ſo in that other Region they add to their Degrees of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and are promoted to farther Acceſſions, and Degrees, and Stations of Happineſs and Glory, till they come to the State of Spirits of juſt Men made perfect.</q> Now in all theſe Varieties of States is there nothing capable of receiving Benefit by the Prayers of the Living? Is there no Communion of Saints between thoſe in the Body, and thoſe out of the Body? But if there be, how can it better be exerciſed or expreſſed than in the ſolemn Offices of the Church?</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Common Sentiments of the Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> becauſe it would be too long to recite ſo many Teſtimonies in this place, and they are collected already to my hand by <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> and others, I need but refer the Reader to them. But this alſo is confeſſed and aſſerted by <hi>Blondel</hi> and <hi>Dalle;</hi> but they would have us believe that they received them from an Impoſtor, a Counterfeit <hi>Sibyl,</hi> a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, impudent and impious Calumny.</p>
            <p>The Agreement with <hi>plain Scriptures</hi> is obſervable in that expreſſion of our Saviour concerning the Sin which ſhall not be forgiven, neither in this World, neither in the World to come, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. and that which agrees with this, of being caſt into Priſon, and not coming out by any means, till Payment of the laſt Farthing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.25. Priſoners of Hope, <hi>Zechar.</hi> 9.11, 12. Sins blotted out when the times of Refreſhing ſhall come, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. Such as ſhew the Incertainty of many Souls in their ſeparate State, even ſuch as were Profeſſors of a high Form in this World, of what their final Doom ſhall be at that Day, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. and 25.44, 45. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Recompence of Rewards at that day, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.14.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which if our confident Oppoſers had ſufficiently conſidered, one would think they ſhould not have preſumed to make ſo light of that middle State, as for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Parties to deprive ſo many Souls there of all Benefit they might receive by their ſurviving Friends here; which many <hi>Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> even among Proteſtants, do frequently ſignifie.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41225:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41225:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41225:26"/>
            <p>The <hi>Practice of the Jews</hi> I have noted already, and ſhall add only here, That in Diſcourſe lately with one of them, he aſſured me that the <hi>Form</hi> they now uſe for that purpoſe is generally believed by all to have been compoſed by <hi>Ezra</hi> and the <hi>Great Congregation.</hi> I there alſo remembred an inſtance of <hi>the Practice of the Apoſtles</hi> themſelves in <hi>St. Paul's Prayer</hi> for <hi>Oneſiphorus,</hi> in ſuch a Form as is hardly to be met with for any Perſon living, however proves it not in vain to Pray for any Perſon, of whom there is Hope, but not Certainty, till that day. So that tho' our great Man, with more Conſidence, I doubt, than Conſcience, and without any Proof or Reaſon at all, doth poſitively affirm him then living, <hi>p.</hi> 210. he gets nothing at all by it.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee in this a Univerſal Agreement in all things: but, on the contrary, if we examine <hi>the Obſtinate Oppoſition</hi> of it throughout, we ſhall find nothing ſolid and conſiſtent in it; neither with Truth, nor Honeſty, nor any good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: but a plauſible Pretence of the Pure Word of God to cover an impure Inclination and Deſire to ſet aſide the Authority which God inſtituted, and ſet up themſelves and their own Conceits in the place of it. 2. Inconſiſtent with it ſelf; firſt, denying or cavilling at the Antiquity or Univerſality of the Practice; and then, when they thought they had found out an Evaſion, confeſſing that, which they could no longer for ſhame deny, and betaking themſelves to their new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention: 3. Inconſiſtent with the Sincerity, Simplicity, and Ingenuity of the Goſpel, in their ſhameleſs Shuffles, Cavils and Evaſions; of which I have noted divers, and many more might be obſerved; but there is one not to be omitted here; their alleadging the Writings of <hi>Epiphanius, Chryſoſtome, Auguſtin,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, againſt not only their own, but the confeſſed ancient Practice of the Church in their time, in this Caſe: Inconſiſtent with that Modeſty, Reſpect and Decency which the Goſpel requires toward all, in their Cenſuring as <hi>delirous,</hi> not only ſome particular Perſons, but generally all the moſt Holy, Ancient Chriſtians, in what was their common Sentiments, and is believed by the moſt learned of the <hi>Church of England</hi> to be plainly taught in the Holy Scriptures: 5. Inconſiſtent with that Reverence and Regard that Chriſtians ſhould have for the Honour of the Church of Chriſt, his Promiſes to it, and Care of it, in ſo foul and ſcandalous an Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that they received their common Notions of the preſent State of ſeparate Souls in the other World from an Impoſtor; which, was not their Impudence therein as notorious as it is groundleſs, and deſtitute of any proof at all, might prove a Tentation to unſettled Souls, to ſuſpect all to be no better: And for other Conſequences, it is plain they lead the way to all others to reject their own uſurped Authority with the ſame Eaſe and Impudence that they do that of the Church of Chriſt; and to ſet up their own Conceits againſt theirs, and pretend Scripture for it; and ſo to an endleſs Courſe of Separations, Schiſms, Sects and Confuſions; and, in concluſion, ſet up that Authority over others, which they themſelves in the mean time reject; as by their <hi>Synod of Dort,</hi> and others in <hi>France</hi> appears: And beſides all this, it is much to be feared, that they lead multitudes of Souls into that miſerable Security and Preſumption, wherewith our Saviour hath acquainted us that many will find themſelves deceived at that day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. And therefore if theſe be not pertinacious Schiſmaticks and Hereticks, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things to draw away Diſciples after them, and therefore carefully to be avoided, I know not who are; or what ſo many Cautions in the Scripture to that purpoſe do ſignifie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41225:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
